<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Pomander of prayer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1530</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25421.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124473</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">57402363</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 57402363</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2172:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Pomander of prayer.</title>
                  <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <p>
                     <name type="place">Jmprented at London in the Fetestrete [sic] / at the sygne of the Rose garlande/ by Robert Coplande.,</name>
                     <date>The yere of our lorde .M.CCCCC.xxx. the .xxxi. day of October. [1530].</date>
                  </p>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Different from Thomas Becon's work of same title--Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Author described as "one of the deuout fathers of the Charterhous of Shene"--P. [6].</note>
                  <note>Edited by Richard Whitford--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McK. 77) follows colop.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]⁴ A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title page and t.p. verso illus.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:1"/>
            <p>¶The Pomander of prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>monk kneeling to left of cross, praying to Jesus, who stands to right of cross ("Christ as man of sorrows being adored by a Carthusian"--British Library description)</figDesc>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e peto mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am et non iudicium:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Fili fuge vince tace quieſce</p>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The greateſt comfort in al temptacyon.</l>
                     <l>Is the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of cryſtes paſſyon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>"St. Bridget of Sweden" (identified by F.C. Francis in "Three Unrecorded English Books of the Sixteenth Century," The Library, vol. s4-XVII, issue 2 [Sept. 1936]: 191)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:2"/>
            <head>¶An exhortacion to the reders by a broder of Syon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſyderyng the myſery and infelicite of this our mooſt peryllous tyme / how the flode of ſynne hath ouer ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> charyte and peas is almooſt extynct fayth dyſperſed / hope dyſſolued / vertue &amp; pyte outlawed / ſanctyte annulled / preſthode dyſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / relygyon decayed. In maner no conſtancy in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peple / no fydelyte betwene neyghbour &amp; neyghbour neyther in byeng nor ſellyng / nor any other contract. One ſcantly may truſt another. And now ſuche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exceſſe of glotony / and ſo the people dooth nouryſſhe theyr bodyes: that abſtynence is banyſſhed / and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery exalted. Vyrgyns hath loſt theyr dyamonde of ſhamefaſtnes / and haue founde the rayle of boldnes / whiche is the noryce of wantonnes. Matrymony is torned the luſt of the body. wolde god it were not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in to aduoutry. where vpon our mooſt holy fader in heuen / whiche was wonte with his ſwete rodde to correct vs. Now ſore agreued and dyſpleaſed with vs / maketh his terryble ſworde of Iuſtyce ouer vs. yea dayly with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame dooth bete vs with famyne / derth / and peſtylence. with ſodayn dethe and ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſekeneſſe in in oure bodyes. And all this is for the ſynne of our bodyes. And ouer all theſe with innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mo myſeryes. what dyuyſyon is amonge the prynces and heedes of the chyrche / I reporte me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. I do feare me to the great hurte and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of the people. But very aſſured I am that
<pb facs="tcp:181163:3"/> it is to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great domage of grace / &amp; loſſe of many a ſoule what kynde chylde of god is there in this worlde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeth his fader ſo ſore dyſpleaſed / and alſo his moder the catholycall chyrche ſo ſore decayed / but he wolde be ſory / tremble / and quake / and ſeke alwayes for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy how he myght agayne be reconſyled to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; helpe to redreſſe his moder ſo wounded &amp; dyffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fro the heed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fote I wote not in what degre or ſtate of Cryſtes chyrch I may ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is the lyfe / the helthe / &amp; the conuerſacion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde be and hath bene in chryſtianite / our lorde Ieſu remedy it / &amp; helpe it. For onely the werke of his inſuꝑable mercy it muſte nedes be. for it paſſeth the power of man / for of mannes behalfe I ſe no remedy / but penaunce and prayer. And now the hertes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people be ſo ſore deie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; conuerted to the aſfeccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this worlde. &amp; ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely enco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſtudy &amp; beſyneſſe therof / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr hertes can not pray. But whyles theyr moder dooth pray / theyr hartes be full of worldly cogytacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of mynd. They many tymes agaynſt theyr wylles (to the great loſſe of the fruyt of theyr prayer) whiche yf it were pure nothynge myght reſyſte it / it wolde aſcende to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne of god as ſcrypture ſayth. And fro thens it wolde not departe whyle it had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> petycion.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cle. xxxv.</note> For as ſaynt Auſtyn ſayth. Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prayer of many ſhall not be herde.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d fratres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>heremo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.xliiii. et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. Ad ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. xv. luce.</note> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it dooth ꝓcede of pure &amp; meke hertes. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell of Cryſt dooth ſhewe vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> importune pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuall perſeuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng ſeme im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſyble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we aſke of god <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le.xxxv.</note> / it wyll at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte in lyne the eare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god &amp; opteyne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort / as he ſhewed in the parable of .iij. loues. And not withſtandyng
<pb facs="tcp:181163:3"/> that we be not his frendes: but wretches &amp; ſynners: and therefore by reaſon of our ſynne he ſeeth in vs no cauſe to haue pyte on vs. yet contynuall prayer wyll vaynquyſſhe him / &amp; inclyne his mercy &amp; charyte to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue our neceſſytees ſatyſfy: and our requeſtes.<note place="margin">Luce. xviii</note> As he ſhewed hymſelfe in the ſymilytude of the wydowe &amp; the vnryght wyſe iudge / whyche for the wydowes importune and contynuall cry and clamour was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled &amp; fayne to gyue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with her.<note place="margin">pſ. xc clam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uit adme. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> So god wyll do / for ſo he promyſed vnto his people. with what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſynne / temptacyon / ſekeneſſe / loſſe of goodes / or other aduerſyte of the worlde we be vexed / call and pray perſeuerauntly and we ſhall haue conforte.<note place="margin">luce. xviii.</note> But he byddeth vs to pray and ceaſe not. But alas for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prayer is in maner gone. I mene the contynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally affeccyon / mynde / &amp; deſyre to god &amp; godly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> habundaunce of dedes of pyte &amp; almes / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to theyr abylite. For who hath theſe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally dooth pray as this treatyſe folowyng more lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely dooth declare. And ſheweth alſo what is prayer and how we ſholde order our prayer. &amp; our ſelfe in the tyme of prayer. And howe we ſholde make our pety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many other great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytees &amp; benefytes whiche cometh by prayer. And ſpecyally remedyes agaynſt wandryng myndes &amp; vayne cogytacyons in tyme of prayer / whiche premyſſes conſyderyng / &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng how charyte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people is now very colde.<note place="margin">eccle. xxix.</note> And almes which hyd in the boſom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore was wont to pray inſtauntly / but now hath ceaſed / for lytell is gyuen in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſpecte as it hath bene. Therfore I was very glad y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this treatyſe fortuned to come to my han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / ſyth I founde it bothe good / deuout / fruytfull / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:181163:4"/> catholycall / thynkyng how many hertes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſholde be moche conforted therin / dyde cauſe it to be imprynted. And ſo moche more rather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er and auctour of it / is one of the deuout fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cartherhous of Shene. whoſe vertue and lernynge is well approued. wherfore deuout reder I counſell the to bye this ſwete treatyſe / &amp; exercyſe thy ſelfe orde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge thy ſelfe there after. And I doubt not but thou ſhalt do moche honoure to god / ſuffrage to all cryſten people / and to thy ſelfe moche profyte and edyfyeng. whiche almyghty god graunt to all the reders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>¶Here foloweth the table and chapytres of this preſent treatyſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>¶The prologue of the treatyſe folowynge.</item>
               <item>¶The preface.</item>
               <item>¶The dyffynycyon of prayer. Capitulo. i.</item>
               <item>¶That we ſholde oft tymes vſe prayer. Ca. ij.</item>
               <item>¶Of the profyte that cometh by prayer. Ca. iij.</item>
               <item>¶Of .iij. thynges neceſſary to be conſydered afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge of prayer. Ca. iiij.</item>
               <item>¶How there is two maners of prayers: of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych one is called vocall / &amp; the other mentall. Ca. v.</item>
               <item>¶Of .ij. thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges neceſſaryly req<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ired to prayer. Ca. vi.</item>
               <item>¶Of certayne thynges that wyll gyue a man occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon to prayer. Ca. vij.</item>
               <item>¶How in tyme of prayer ſomtyme the mynde is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che diſtraught by reaſon of worldly beſynes. And remedyes for the ſame. Ca. viij.</item>
               <item>¶Of other maner of diſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And the cauſes: and
<pb facs="tcp:181163:4"/> remedyes of the ſame. Ca. ix.</item>
               <item>¶How a man may order hymſelfe in tyme of prayer Ca. x.</item>
               <item>¶How after prayer wyll folow te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyons of vayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory. And how they may be eſchewed &amp; auoyded by dyuers remedyes. Ca. xi.</item>
               <item>¶Howe the fynall intente of our prayers ſholde be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laude &amp; prayſe of good. And how we may lawfully deſyre in prayer all other thynges neceſſary / refer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge them to this ende. Ca. xij.</item>
               <item>¶For whome we ſholde pray. Ca. xiij.</item>
               <item>¶How he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll haue his prayer aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to god muſt make it .ij. wynges. Ca. xiiij.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth this preſent table.
<figure>
                  <figDesc>"Salvator mundi" (identified by F.C. Francis in "Three Unrecorded English Books of the Sixteenth Century," The Library, vol. s4-XVII, issue 2 [Sept. 1936]: 191): Christ blessing with right hand and holding orb surmounted by cross in left hand; top left, God the Father (?); top right, a dove representing the Holy Ghost (?)</figDesc>
                  <head>Reſpice in facie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i</abbr>
                        <expan>Christi</expan>
                     </choice> tui</head>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>"Christ with the instruments of the Passion" (identified by F.C. Francis in "Three Unrecorded English Books of the Sixteenth Century," The Library, vol. s4-XVII, issue 2 [Sept. 1936]: 191)</figDesc>
                  <p>¶The pardon for .v. pater nr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. aues &amp; a crede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pyteous beholdynge of theſe armes is .xxxii. M. &amp; .lv. yeres.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> man vnkynde</l>
               <l>Bere in thy mynde</l>
               <l>My paynes ſmerte</l>
               <l>And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt fynde</l>
               <l>Me true and kynde</l>
               <l>Lo here my herte.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:5"/>
            <head>¶The prologue of the treatyſe folowynge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god I intende in this tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atyſe folowynge to ſhewe howe a man ought to order hymſelfe in tyme of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer / and what ſholde be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fynall intent therof / &amp; for what thynges I thynke it mooſt expedient for to pray. But fyrſt of all I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what is prayer after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyffinycion of ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyn / and this in the fyrſt chapytre. In the ſeconde chapytre that a man ſholde oft tymes vſe prayer. In the thyrde chapytre of the prouffite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cometh therby In the .iiij. chapytre of .iij. thyngꝭ neceſſary to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered tofore the begynnyng of prayer. After this I ſhall ſpeke of two maner of prayers / that is to ſay / of mentall prayer / &amp; vocal prayer. The which ſaynt Bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture deuydeth in to two partes / that is in to pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vocall prayer / &amp; myxte vocal prayer. which is one and whyche is the other / it ſhall be declared in theyr places. But my ſpecyall intent &amp; meanynge is mooſt of the myxte prayer. For that (as I ſuppoſe) is mooſt neceſſary for to be vſed of ſuche perſones for whome I wryte this treatyſe. But ꝑaduenture ſome men wyll meruayle why I dyd not wryte this matter in latin ſtyle (for then it myght haue bene vnderſtande of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny perſones: as well of alyens as of this lande) but in englyſſhe / the whiche but fewe / that is to ſay one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly englyſſhe men / or ſuche as haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſaunt in englande do vnderſtande. The cauſe is this. I was deſyre bothe of lerned and of vnlerned to wryte this treatyſe. Not for the lerned (for they vnderſtande ſcrypture / and knowe this matter better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I) but
<pb facs="tcp:181163:6"/> for the vnlerned that lacke knowlege of holy ſcryptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / to inſtruct them in the order of prayer. That is to ſay / to ſhewe them for whome / or what thynges it is mooſt expedyent to pray / and what ſholde moeue them to pray deuoutly / and gyue them occaſyon to perceuer therin / with ſuche other as ſhall be contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſayd treatyſe folowyng. ¶Now I haue made anſwere to ſuche poyntes as may be obiected of ſome quycke wytted perſones. I wyll beſeche the deuout chryſtyans for whome I haue taken this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour / and wryten this matter at theyr deſyre to the honour of god / and to the profyte of theyr ſoules and myne / to loke vpon it ſubſtancyally. And not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with redynge it ones ouer / but kepe it with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contynually / vſyng oft to rede it ouer / vnto ſuche tyme as they be very perfyte therin / for I truſte the after that they rede it the better they ſhall lyke it. ¶And lyke as a Pomaunder whan it is chauſted &amp; made warme with contynuaunce in a mannes han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de gyueth a fragrant and ſwete ſmell / ſo I truſt this Pomaunder of prayer (for ſo I wyll this treatyſe be named) yf it be ofte tymes loked on and redde wyth good purpoſe to practyſe ſuche thynges as ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned therin / wyll gyue a fragraunt ſmell of ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conuerſacyon and lyuynge to the deuout reders of it. The whiche yf it ſo do / I pray the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gyue laude and prayſynge to god therfore. And contrary wyſe where any thynge is amyſſe aſcrybe it (I pray the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to my inſuffycyency and ignoraunce / whiche lacke bothe lernynge and eloquence. ¶Fynally I beſeche all them ſpecyally that ſhall profyce by this poore tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atyſe / to pray for me a wretche / whiche hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:181163:6"/> this laboure to the honour of god and theyr edyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng / that I may worke in myne owne lyfe theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccyons that I haue gathered &amp; wryten for them And I ſhall praye for them by the grace of god / who euer be with them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>¶Emanuel. ¶The preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F late tyme I haue ben inſtauntly deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of certayne ſpyrytuall fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſome treatyſe that myght be inducty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and alſo demonſtratyue (to ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout perſones as lacke lernyng and knowlege of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcrypture) howe &amp; vnder what maner they myght order them ſelfe in prayer. To the performacyon of this charytable deſyre and requeſt I knowe my ſelfe vnworthy and vnable / bothe for lacke of ſpeculacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and practyſe therof. Not withſtandynge I wyll deſyre my ſolycytares in this matter to call with me to our ſauyour Ieſu Cryſt / ſaynge as one of this dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples dyde. Domine doce nos orare.<note place="margin">Luce. xi.</note> That is to ſay Lorde or mayſter teche vs to pray. This done I ſhall ſtudy with dylygence / ſome thynge to ſatyſfye theyr deſyre / as it ſhall pleaſe our foreſayd mayſter Ieſu to gyue me grace.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:7"/>
            <head>¶The dyffynycyon of prayer. Ca. i.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.cc. xxxix. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt I thynke it very expedient to ſhewe you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyffynicion of prayer that ye may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better knowe what it is. Saynt Auſtyn ſayth. Quid autem eſtoratio: niſi aſcentio ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terreſtribꝰ ad celeſtia: inquiſitio ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan>: inuiſibilium deſiderium? As who ſholde ſay. Prayer is nothynge elles but an aſcencyon of the ſoule from erthly thynges to heuenly thynges that be aboue / &amp; a deſyre of thynges inuyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. ¶we may take this dyffynycion that whan we pray we ſhold not wylfully ſuffer the affeccion of our myndes to reſt on worldly creatures / but we ſholde haue our deſyres eleuate vnto god omnipotent in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And this appereth well in the begynnynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayer the whiche Cryſt dyde teche to his dyſciples: where as we ſay. Pater noſter qui es i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celis: ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficetur nomen tuum.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>thei. vi.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> O our fader the whiche arte in heuen / ſantyfied be thy name. This worde. In celis (as ſayth the gloſe ordynary) is put there bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſholde in tyme of prayer eleuat our myndes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirituall heuyns / where as is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fader omnipotent mooſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in his glory. we ſholde ſo order our ſelfe in prayer that we myght truely ſay with the apoſtle ſaynt Poule.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d philip. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>x.</note> Noſtra autem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio in celis eſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶That we ſholde oft tymes vſe prayer. Ca. ij.</head>
            <p>IN many &amp; dyuers places of holy ſcrypture we be exhorted and prouoked to frequentacyon of
<pb facs="tcp:181163:7"/> prayer. It is wryten.<note place="margin">Ad col. iii.</note> Orationibꝰ inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in eis in gratiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> actione. Vſe you to pray inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly / not ſlepyngly / nor ſlouthfully / but quykly &amp; deuoutly gyuyng thankes and prayſynges to god. ¶It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wryten. Subditus eſto dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o: et ora eum.<note place="margin">Pſal. xxxv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Subdue thyſelfe man to thy lorde god / &amp; make thy prayers to hym. ¶Alſo. Non impediaris orare ſemper.<note place="margin">Eccle xvii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Lete nothyng be impedyment to the / but that thou mayſt be euer in prayer. ¶Alſo our ſauyour Cryſt in the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpell of Luke. Oportet ſemper orare et no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deficere.<note place="margin">Luce. xviii</note> ye ſhold euer be prayeng &amp; neuer ceaſe. ¶And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle ſaynt Poule. Sine interceſſione orate.<note place="margin">1. Ad theſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> v.</note> That is to ſay Pray you and ceaſe not. ¶And alſo ad Timotheum. Volo ergo viros orare in omni loco. I wyl that men be prayeng in euery place. But bycauſe theſe wordes ſoundeth to be veray ſtreyte / yf we take the lytterall ſence of them. For it is very harde / and almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble for any man euer to contynue in actuall prayer. A certayne holy doctour expoundyng ſayeth.<note place="margin">Beda ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lu cam ca. xvii.</note> Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> de ſinit orare niſi qui deſinit bn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>facere. As long as a man is doyng any good dedes: ſo longe he is prayeng. And except he ceaſe from doyng good dedes: he ceaſeth not to pray. This expoſycion maketh the wordes before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd eaſy / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth the reders or herers of this. yet not withſtandyng I wyll exhorte euery deuout chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyan to gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf to vocal prayer as nygh as they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyently &amp; expedyently. For doubtleſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wyll come grete profyte and manyfolde fruytes / of the whiche by the grace of god parte I ſhall bryefly and ſhortly touche</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of the profyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cometh by prayer. Ca. iii.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>omeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lxxviii.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy doctour ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſoſtome ſaith. Magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vere bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chariſſimi or<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o. &amp;c To bryng you in moche latyn it is grete la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour to me / &amp; but lytell profyte or none to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reders. For my purpoſe is ſpecially to wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te to ſuch ꝑſones as be vnlerned / &amp; not to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. wherefore here after I ſhall leue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latyn &amp; ſpeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſence therof in englyſſhe / truſtyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhal be more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pendyous to me / &amp; more acceptable to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for whome I wryte. ¶This doctour Chriſoſtom ſayth. Prayer is a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of grete vertu &amp; goodneſſe. For if ye take gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ꝓfyte by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is approbate &amp; ſinguler in <abbr>vtues</abbr>. How moche more (ſaith he) ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſone haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in his prayer ſpeketh to god / the which is the lorde &amp; gyuer of all vertues?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. xxx. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. e.</note> Saynt Auguſtyn ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prayer dooth call the grace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis ſoule / it putteth away all hardnes of hertt yt maketh faſtynge &amp; abſtyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be dulcet &amp; delectable to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſoule. And lyke as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not make a ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte refeccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or meale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out drynke / ſo faſtynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out prayer can not ꝑfytely nouryſſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule. Prayer cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth a ꝑſone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in deedly ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on to ryſe fro his ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / &amp; to be made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde of ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Prayer (as ſayth Ludolphe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carthuſian in a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayn ſermon) is a vertue ineſtymable / &amp; of ſuffycyent efficacy to i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petrate &amp; gete all thyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is good / &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtande all thynge that is not good. By prayer we obtayne pacyence in all ſekeneſſes / dyſeaſes / and aduerſytees. By prayer we may ſubdue all euell af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. By prayer we may perceyue the ſubtyltees and dyſceytes of our gooſtly enmyes / &amp; be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſt and auoyde them. By prayer we may gladly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre
<pb facs="tcp:181163:8"/> &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly bere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out tedyouſnes all penyte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyall la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours &amp; afflyccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. By prayer we may be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte in the ſwete excercyſes of ſpyrytuall lyuyng. By prayer we may refreyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſtyall &amp; carnall appety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of our bodyes. By prayer we may eſchewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctacyon of vayne thoughtes. By prayer we may ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyſſhe our hertes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant purpoſe &amp; ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of god. Prayer is moche ꝓfytable at eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry neceſſyte / for by it we may remoue &amp; expel fro vs al wycked ſpyrytes / &amp; call for our helpe &amp; conſolacyon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloryous aungels of heuen. For as ſaynt Bede ſayth Lyke as a thefe dooth fle away wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour or noyſe of his reſyſtenes: ſo doth our gooſtly en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clamour of prayer. And lyke as theyr neybours come at theyr callyng to help them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of theues / ſo do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels of god come to helpe vs agaynſt our enmyes whan we cal to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by prayer. The manyfolde affliccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Pharao by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayer of Moyſes were euer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſraell murmured ayenſt god in deſert ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes he puniſſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyre / ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brennyng ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme by other mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it were to long to ſpeke now / but euer whan Moyſes prayed for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our lorde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drewe his ſworde of ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fro the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By prayer kynge Dauyd was delyuered fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Saul &amp; Abſolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By prayer Helyas obtened of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it dyd not rayne by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of .iij. yeres &amp; .vi. moneths / &amp; than he prayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne for to haue rayn / &amp; it pleaſed god to ſend ſufficy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent therof for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓduccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fruytes &amp; other neceſſaries By prayer Helyzeꝰ dyd reyſe fro dethe to lyfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyld of the Sunamyte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whome he had his hoſpitalyte.
<pb facs="tcp:181163:9"/> It wolde aſke a longe ſpace to ſpeke of all the myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and other thynges that the prophetes and other good men of the olde lawe / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles with other true chryſtyans of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe lawe hath optened of god by the vertue of prayer. wherfore I wyll lete them paſſe / prayeng you my ſpyrytuall frendes to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with theſe fewe / the whiche I haue now ſhortly touched. And for a breue concluſyon of this matter I ſhall brynge one auctoryte of the goſpell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dooth ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly expreſſe what ꝓfite come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th by prayer / though there were no mo in all holy ſcrypture but onely it. Our mayſter Chryſt in the goſpell of Marke ſayeth. Quecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> orantes petitis:<note place="margin">Capitulo. xi</note> credite <choice>
                  <abbr>qr</abbr>
                  <expan>quia</expan>
               </choice> accipietis: et eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nient vobis. That is to ſay. what ſoeuer ye right wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſly deſyre of me by prayer / beleue that ye ſhal haue it and ye ſhall haue it after / your deſyre / or elles moche better / &amp; more for your profyte. Therfore ſeynge that prayer is of ſo grete dygnyte / &amp; ſo acceptable to god lete vs not forgete to pray / but lete vs occupy our ſelfs therin / as moche as we may conuenyently. But per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aduenture ſome men of the worlde wyll ſay. Prayer is ordeyned to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templatyf and relygious perſones: for they haue nothyng elles to be occupyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lete them pray. But we that be men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde haue other beſyneſſe to do / and therfore we may not be euer rennyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche to make our prayers. It ſhall be ſuffycye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs to pray on the holy dayes. I feare me leſt there be many of this faculte nowe of dayes / more is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pyte. And I thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cauſe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of is blyndneſſe of hert ingendred by cuſtome of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. From y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche to be delyuered our moder holy chyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dooth pray ſayeng. A cecitate cordys libera nos
<pb facs="tcp:181163:9"/> domine. I knowe not what it ſhold auayle to exhort ſuche perſones to prayer / except they wolde fyrſt pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge theyr ſoules from this blyndneſſe by contricion / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſyon / &amp; ſatyſfaccion / yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandyng yf they wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de fall to prayer / by the vertue therof / they myght ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne grace to ryſe the more quyckely from theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full lyuyng. But my purpoſe as now is to wryte ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to ſuche deuout perſones / as I truſt wyl not to theyr knowlege reſt in deedly ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / for all the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lucres of this worlde. And I truſt of that dyſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon there be ryght many. whoſe nomber I beſeche our lorde to multyply &amp; encreaſe. Theſe deuout ſoules I wyll counſell oft tymes to vſe prayer / &amp; not to make ſuche excuſes as the other perſones beforeſaid do. For as ſayth ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſoſtome in his foreſayd ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myly it is no ſuffycient excuſe to ſay they may not be euer at the chyrche to pray For a man that is well dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpoſed may pray in any place where ſoeuer he is. For it is neyther the place nor the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is impedyment to prayer. ¶If a man neyther lyft vp his handes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde the heuens / nor knele on his knees / nor make tunſyon on his breſt / yet ſhall he make a parfyte pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er / yf he rendre to god onely a feruent &amp; deuout myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. That man that is come of noble blode &amp; ryall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny may be at lyberte to frequentate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche and other ſecrete places at his pleaſure for his deuocyon. And therfore may he the more quyetly gyue hymſel e to vocall prayer. And not onely wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is ſecrete / but alſo wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany he may vſe to pray / though his prayers be than the ſhorter. As (for an example) whan he ſytteth at dyner / or ſouper / or whan he is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymes at other honeſt recreacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: he may lyft vp his
<pb facs="tcp:181163:10"/> hert vnto god ſayeng in his mynde / though he ſpeke nothyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mouthe. Ieſu haue mercy vpon me / &amp; forgyue me all my ſynnes. Ieſu gyue me grace to be thy true and faythfull ſeruaunt. Ieſu make me to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the with all my hert / &amp; all my ſoule. with ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as it ſhall pleaſe god to put in his mynde / ſomety<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes ſayng one / &amp; ſomtymes another. And yf it pleaſe hym to ſpeke with his mouthe he may ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes ſaye. Aue benigne Ieſu. And ſomtymes. Aue maria. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche other ſhorte prayers as ſhall come to his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / the whiche ſaynt Auguſtyn calleth Or<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ones iaculatories / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye / prayers iaculatory: or redy at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande. And they be very profytable &amp; expedyent to obteyne grace. Thus may the man of worſhyp oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy himſelfe in prayer. Other men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be of inferyous degrees whyther they be marchauntes / yomen / or craftes men or of what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycyon ſoeuer they be they can not be excuſed / but they may vſe moche prayer yf they wyll. For yf they be ryding or goyng in iourney they may haue ſpace ynough therto / yf they be at ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me at theyr occupacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ſellyng of theyr ware / yet may they vſe ſuch ſhort prayers as I haue beforeſaid in theyr ſhoppes or other places where they be. For god regardeth more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hert &amp; mynde of him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayeth tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where he prayeth. The prophete Hieremy beyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foule pryſon / &amp; ſtandyng in clay &amp; dyrt / made his prayers to god. Danyell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lake of lyons dyde alſo pray to god. Ionas beyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bely of a grete fyſſhe dyde not forgete to pray. The thefe han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng on the croſſe at the ryght hande of Cryſt made his prayer in fewe wordes. Iob ſytting on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghyl dyde offer vp his prayers to god. And all they by the
<pb facs="tcp:181163:10"/> merites of theyr prayers was herde of god / and they obteyned theyr deſyres to theyr grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacyon and confort. Here may ye ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god dooth accept the douout prayer of man in what place ſoeuer it is ſayd. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my intyerly beloued frendes: lete vs exercyſe our ſelfes in prayer as moch as we may / neuer deferryng it for the tyme nor for the place. For euery tyme / &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry place is apt &amp; conuenyent for prayer. For yf we gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue our ſelfe thus to prayer / I truſt in the goodneſſe of god we ſhall taſte of the holſome &amp; ſwete fruytes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth therof / of the whiche parte I haue ſhortly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched here before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of .iij. thynges neceſſary to be conſydered afore the begynnynge of prayer. Ca. iiij.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the mynde of the mellyfluous doctor ſaynt Bernarde in his boke of ſentences: it is neceſſary for euery perſone to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder thre thynges tofore the begynnynge of theyr prayer. Fyrſt what thynge they in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende to aſke in prayer. Secondaryly of whome they aſke. Thyrdly themſelfe that do aſke. ¶As to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt partye I ſaye / it is neceſſary to conſyder before theyr prayer / what thynge they intende to aſke in prayer / leeſt peraduenture they ſholde aſke that thynge that ſhold be contrary vnto charyte / as the dethe of theyr enemyes / domage of theyr neyghbours / or other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. He that ſo prayed deſerueth not for to be herde of god.<note place="margin">Ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For he in the goſpell of ſaynt Luke / the ſyxt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre doth exhorte vs for to loue our euyll wyllers or
<pb facs="tcp:181163:11"/> enmyes / and to be benefycyall to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do hate vs / and to pray for them that wrongfully do ꝑſecute vs. But yf we pray for the remyſſyon of our ſynnes / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt / for vertue / for ſpiritual wyſdom for faythe / for trouthe / for iuſtyce / for mekenes / for pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyence / &amp; for ſuche other / than almyghty god of his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fynyte goodneſſe wyll quykly here vs / &amp; graunt our deſyre. For of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in prayer aſketh ſuche thynges almyghty god ſpeketh by his prophete Eſay ſayeng.<note place="margin">Ca. lxv.</note> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be ſpekyng I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l here them / &amp; tofore the &amp; begyn to crye I ſhall gracyouſly here the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ¶Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daryly we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder of whom we aſke any thyng by prayer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluacyon of our ſoules. For we ought to haue afore our eyes as the onely graunter &amp; gyuer of our peticion. That is to ſay god omnypote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And in hym we muſt conſyder .ij. thynges / his infenite good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe / &amp; his ſuperexcellent mageſty. His goodneſſe by the whiche he wyll frely graunt vs oure deſyre. And this ſhall cauſe vs to haue a grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fydence &amp; truſt in hym. His mageſty by the whiche he may graunt / &amp; gyue what ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe hym. And this ſhall cauſe vs to gyue honour and reuerence to hym / as it beſemeth the creature to gyue to hym that dyde crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; make hym. ¶Thyrdly we muſt conſyder our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes who &amp; what we be that do aſke any thyng of god by prayer / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be wretches of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde and greuous ſynners / deſeruyng to obtene nothyng that we pray for / as of our owne merytes: but onely by the grete mercy &amp; goodneſſe of god. And this wyll cauſe vs to humylyate &amp; meke our ſelfes in the ſyght of god / and than we may be ſure that he wyll not dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſe our prayers.<note place="margin">Pſ. C.i.</note> For the prophete ſayth. Our lorde
<pb facs="tcp:181163:11"/> hath loked on meke men: &amp; he hath not diſpyſed theyr prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶How there is two maner of prayers: of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che one is called vocall &amp; the other mentall. Ca v.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E rede by a holy doctour of .ij. maner of prayers: of the whiche one is called vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prayer / &amp; the other is called me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall prayer. Vocall prayer is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / the whiche is ſpoken by mouyng of the tongue &amp; of the lyppes: &amp; by pronouncyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Of this pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer ſpeketh the ꝓphete in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iij. pſalme / ſayeng. Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce mea ad dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m clamaui: et exaudiuit mede mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ſcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuo. I cryed to our lorde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my voyce / &amp; he herde me from his holy hyll. And alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xvij. pſalme. In tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatione mea inuocaui dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m: et ad deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meum clama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ui. Et exaudiuit de templo ſcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuo vocem meam. &amp;c In my trybulacion I inwardly called our lorde / &amp; I cryed to my god / &amp; it pleaſed hym from his holy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to here my voyce. ¶After the mynde of ſaynt Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture in his thyrde queſtyon vpon the .xiiij. dyſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction / in the .iiij. boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentences: vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prayer may be deuyded in to .ij. partes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay in to pure vocall prayer / &amp; in to myxte vocall prayer. Pure vocall prayer is whan a man ſpeketh the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des with his mouthe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any affeccyon or deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde ꝑteynyng therto. And this is but of ſmall meryte &amp; lytell effect / yf there be no intencyon actuall nor virtuall goyng tofore / but yf it haue an intencion goyng tofore / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay yf a man at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng of his prayer lyft vp his mynde to god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:181163:12"/> to pray deuoutly / than is this prayer merytoryous / though his mynde afterwarde by fraylte be not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che theron / it is ſuffycye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to excuſe a man of his duty.</p>
            <p>¶Myxte vocall prayer is that the / whiche is ſpoken with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthe / &amp; procedeth fro the herte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ardaunt deuocyon &amp; feruent affeccyon of the mynde. This ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of prayer is very good &amp; ꝓfytable / and gretely ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepted in the ſyght of almyghty god. And vnto ſuche ꝑſones y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perceyue theyr deuocyon to encreaſe by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwete wordes in prayer / this myxte prayer is comynly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſte / and this I thynke dooth fortune mooſt oft in good deuout people of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde (for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me I ſpecyally wryte this treatyſe) the which haue a good mynde to ſerue god. But yet they haue not ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peryence of the delectable ſpirituall lyfe / nor dyde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer taſte the ſwete delicious wynes of the lyfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>platyfe / whiche god hath reſerueth vnto ſuche perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be as it were ſequeſtrate from the worlde / &amp; the affeccyons thereof / and thrugh the mortyfycacyon of ſenſualyte be made by the grace of god moche ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. ¶The mental prayer (of the whiche here after I intende to ſpeke / as it ſhall pleaſe my mayſter Ieſu for to gyue me grace) I thynke is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt / yf it me vſed ſobrely and dyſcretely. For elles it is ſo laborous and ſo vyolent / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> within ſhort ſpace it wyll brynge a man vnto ſuche debilitacion and weykeneſſe of brayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wyll caſt hym in greate daunger of ſekeneſſe / or ſome other great inconuenyence.</p>
            <p>¶Mentall prayer is that the whyche is offred to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god with perfyte feruour of ſpyryte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocyon
<pb facs="tcp:181163:12"/> of the mynde / without any ſounde of wordes ſpoken by the mouthe This prayer is of grete effecte and profytable yf it be vſed dyſcretely as I ſayd befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. In ſome caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myxte vocall prayer is better to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me perſones than is this. But yf we ſhall ſpeke ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter and without any ſuche reſpect I thynke this mentall prayer is the beſt. For vocal prayer bothe pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; myxte maye be ſpoken and ſayd whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde is occupyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vayne cogytacyons of thynges ſayd or done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / the whiche perteyneth nothyng to theyr prayer. But this mentall prayer is of ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſoo pure nature / that it wyll not at that tyme admyt any other thought that ſholde be impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or lettynge to it. For whan a man prayeth mentally / his mynde is onely therupon / or vpon due cyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces perteynyng therto. And yf any other thought by chaunce do occupye his mynde / for that tyme he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to pray mentally. This prayer is of great excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ad dignite / and is the very true and faythfully am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſſadour betwyxt god and mannes ſoule. For there can none aduerſyte lete hym but he wyll go y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght way to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celeſtyall palays / where as the kynge of all kynges: &amp; lorde of all lordes dooth contynually tary / &amp; there effectuouſly with due honour and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the cauſes of his comynge. yea / and this heuenly meſſager ordereth hymſelfe ſoo wyſely and ſo amya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that the mooſt hygh and almyghtyeſt kyng and emperour wyll not lyghtly denye hym any maner of thynge that he deſyreth. But what ſoeuer he chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably aſketh / this mooſt heuenly kynge gracyouſly graunteth. On this maner prayed Anna the wyfe of Helcana / as it is expreſly manyfeſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byble in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:181163:13"/> fyrſt boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges. whan Hely the preſte dyde be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde her face largely perfuſed with teares of deuocy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. She prayed to god bycauſe ſhe had ben al her lyfe without any fruyte procreate by the ſede of man / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wolde pleaſe his mercy &amp; goodnes to graunt her a ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myght be his true ſeruaunt. ¶As ſhe prayed in this maner Hely ſeyng her lippes moue &amp; heryng no voyce thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe had ben inebryate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drynkynge to moche wyne. It may well be that ſhe was dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken / but not of this materyall wyne made of grapes by the craft of man / but ſhe was dronken with ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall wyne of deuocyon the whiche came fro the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceller of heuen. wherof the holy gooſt / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone in trynite is the tauerner / or vyntener. Of howe blyſſed is he / or ſhe that may be inebryate with this wyne? I beſeche you all my ſpyrituall fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to pray for me a wretche / that I may haue grace ſoo to order my ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may deſerue ſome thynge to caſte of this wyne / to the laude and prayſe of hym that is bothe wyne &amp; vyntener. I mene of this deuout &amp; ſwete me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall prayer / of the whiche to ſpeke a lytell more I hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de it expedyent. wherfore I wyll exhorte ſuche perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that by grace can &amp; may practyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe therin to vſe it with dyſcrecyon. And yf they perceyue them ſelfe ſtrong of nature &amp; may well away therwith / to vſe it oft / but not longe at ones. yf they ꝑceyue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf weyke or feble in brayne / it is good for them to vſe it but lytell. It is a prety craft to pray mentally. And there be (as I ſuppoſe) but fewe that be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in. This arte perteneth mooſt ſpecyally to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyf perſones: &amp; other deuoute ſeculer perſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t knowlege of ſcrypture &amp; ſpyrituall thynges.
<pb facs="tcp:181163:13"/> To other vnlerned perſones it is mooſt profytable to vſe the prayer of mouthe / gyuyng therto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuocion of mynde as moche as they may. And this for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon (as ſayth ſaynt Thomas) it is expedyent for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry perſone to exerciſe and vſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maner of prayer / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be mentall or vocall / in the whiche they fynde mooſt ſweteneſſe and increaſe of deuocyon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of .ij. thynges neceſſaryly requyred to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer. Ca. vi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F that the prayer of man ſhall be pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; acceptable in the ſyght of god / it muſt ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue .ii. ꝓpryetes: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / deuocion &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. ¶Fyrſt I ſay our prayers muſt be offred to god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deuocyon / and with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly affeccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hert &amp; mynde / or elles it is no mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle though we be not herde of hym to whome we pray. For yf a man ſholde make his ſupplycacion to a grete prynce of this worlde in any neceſſary cauſe / ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for hymſelfe or for his frende / &amp; dyd not ſpeke effe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctuouſly nor hertely in the ſayd cauſe / but ſlouthfully &amp; as it were ſlepyngly pronunce his wordes / ſo that the prynce myght well &amp; euydently ꝑceyue that his hert dyde nothyng agre with his wordes: it is to be ſuppoſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde deny his peticion or ſupplicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So lykewyſe whan the excellent prynce of heuen the whiche knoweth the hert &amp; thought of euery ꝑſone / dooth perceyue that in the tyme of prayer our hertes be not conſonaunt with our wordes: it is no maruell though he regarde not our peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or prayers. wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is very expedyent yf our prayers ſhall be acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted
<pb facs="tcp:181163:14"/> of god / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deuer our ſelfs to pray with fervor and deuocion. ¶Of certayne thinges that ſhall giue vs occaſyon to deuocion in tyme of prayer I ſhall ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we you hereafter by the grace of Ieſu. But fyrſt I in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende ſome thynge to ſpeke of the contynuaunce that we ſholde haue in prayer.</p>
            <p>¶Our ſauyour Cryſt in the goſpell of Mathe. dooth prouoke vs nt onely to prayer ſayeng Petite et ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipietis: querite et inuenietis: pulſate et aperietur vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis. That is to ſay. Aſke and ye ſhall haue / ſeche &amp; ye ſhall fynde / knocke &amp; I ſhall ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you. In theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des we may haue a grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence &amp; truſt to obteyne whatſoeuer we ryght wyſly deſyre by prayer. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bydded vs aſke wyll not deny. If he wolde haue denyed / he wolde not haue bydden vs aſke. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſayth ſaynt Auguſtyn (Sermon equite de verbis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i in eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſedin Matheu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>). He that counceyleth thus to aſke / wyll he deny? as who wolde ſaye / no. But ꝑaduenture ſomtymes he wyll not graunt our petycyons by &amp; by / but dyfferre vnto another tyme. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for dyuers cauſes? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche yf I ſholde nowe recyte / they wolde aſke a longe tyme / therfore I wyll lete them paſſe all / excepte one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is mooſt for my purpoſe. ¶After the opynion of dyuers doctours ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes almyghty god deferreth to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> petycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his ſupplycauntes &amp; ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: bycauſe he wolde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue &amp; perſeuer in prayer. For perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce in prayer &amp; in euery good dede is worthy to to haue a grete rewarde / &amp; therfore it is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Qui perſeuerauerit vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in finem hic ſaluꝰ erit.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>athe .x.</note> who that in goodneſſe dooth perſeuer vnto the ende / he ſhal be ſaued. And alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſeueraunce in prayer it is wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten.
<pb facs="tcp:181163:14"/> Eccliaſt. Melior eſt finis orationis: <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> principiſi.<note place="margin">Ca. iii.</note> The ende of prayer is better than the begynnynge. wherfore our mayſter Cryſt ſayth.<note place="margin">luce. xviii.</note> Oportet ſemper orare et non deficere / ye ſholde perſeuer in prayer and not fayle them. Thus dooth our ſauyour Ieſus ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in holy ſcrypture / exhorte vs to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and perſeueraunce in prayer. And he dooth not onely councel vs by his ſwete and confortable wordes: but alſo he prouoketh vs therto by famylyare examples Of the whiche one we rede in the .xviij. chapytre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelyſt Luke. where he ſayeth. Iudex quida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erat in quida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ciuitate. &amp;c. There was a iudge in a certay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cyte the whiche dyde not feare god nor man / vnto whome came a certayne wydow of the ſame cyte / de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyryng hym that ſhe myght haue ryght of her aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary. He deferred and wolde not regarde her wordes of a longe ſeaſon. But yet at the laſte bycauſe of her importunyte he remembred hymſelf &amp; ſayd. Though it be ſo that I drede neyther god nor man / yet for her perſeueraunt inſtaunce and deſyre I wyll ſe that her aduerſary ſhall do her no wronge / leeſt peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture at the laſt through her importunyte ſhe wyll be vnto me moche tedyouſe. This aforeſayd parabole ſpake our ſauyour Ieſu Cryſt for to prouoke vs vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuance of prayer. And in lyke wyſe as the iudge dyde dyfferre by a longe ſpace / and yet at the laſte dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de condeſcende vnto the deſyre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wydowe bycauſe of her contynuyng inſtaunce. So wyll the mooſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous ſader of heuen ſomtyme dyfferre for to graunte ſuche thynges as we doo deſyre of hym by prayer. But yf that we wyll perſeuer alway / and call to him contynually / at the laſt he wyll graunt our petycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:181163:15"/> bycauſe of our importunite. ¶Alſo of this matter we haue another parabole in the goſpell of Luke.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cc. xi.</note> where our ſauyour Cryſt ſayth. Quis veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habebit ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. whiche of you hath a frende &amp; gooth to hym at mydnyght ſayng to hym. My frende I pray you len<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de me .iij. loues of breade / For I haue a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me / &amp; I haue no breade to ſet on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table before him. And he beyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in ſayth anſweryng on this maner. I pray you dyſeaſe me not / for my doores be ſhet / &amp; I and my ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes be all in bed. I can not now ryſe &amp; lende them you. yet he is not contented with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere / but taryeth ſtyll contynually knockyng &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng / and wyll not retorne to his hous tyll he ſpede of his purpoſe. I tell you trouthe (ſayeth oure mayſter Cryſt) yf he wyll not aryſe bycauſe he is his frende / yet for his improbite or his i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>portunyte / at the laſt he wyll aryſe and lende hym as moche breade as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. ¶Se here my goſtly fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des how our louyng lorde &amp; mayſter Ieſus cryſt ſheweth to vs this para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bole to ꝓuoke vs to the ꝑceuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of prayer / whoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell &amp; prouocacyon yf we folowe / vndoubtedly as this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſed his frende to ryſe at mydnyght &amp; len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hym breade. So wyll almyghty god (though he deferre for a tyme) gyue vs al thyng neceſſary / yf we call to hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ꝑfourmaunce of prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of certayne thynges that wyll gyue a man occaſyon to pray deuoutly. Ca. vii.</head>
            <p>I Promyſe here tofore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wolde ſhewe you ol ſuche thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll gyue you occaſyon to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocion in tyme of prayer / wherfore by the gace of Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu
<pb facs="tcp:181163:15"/> now I ſhall do my dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ꝑforme that ꝓmyſſe ¶It is a ſpecyall helpe to deuocyon before your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to make a due preparacyon. Therfore it is wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Ante or<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>onem <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>para ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am tuam. Before thy pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer prepare thy mynde / or thy ſoule therto.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. xviii. ca.</note> But ꝑad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſome men be ignorant / &amp; knowe not howe to prepare them / therfore I ſhall ſhewe them after my ſymple reaſon the maner therof. ¶Fyrſt whan ye in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende to praye / tofore the begynnyng of your prayer: call to mynde parte of the many &amp; grete benefytes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whiche god of his goodneſſe hath ſuffycyently in dued you. As the benefytes of your creacyon / how he created and made your ſoule to his owne ſymylitude or lykeneſſe. Of your rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcyon / howe it pleaſed the ſecond perſone in trynite to come fro the glory in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this vale of myſery / &amp; here to ſuffer grete penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and paynes all the tyme of his lyfe / and at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte mooſt bytter paſſion &amp; dethe on the croſſe / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pcion of you and all mankynde. Of your <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſeruacyon / how that god of his ſinguler gracyouſneſſe hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued you from the fyrſt day of your natyuite to this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tyme / gyuyng you meate &amp; drinke and clothes &amp; all other thinges neceſſary and expedient for you to haue. And beſydes theſe many tymes he hath dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered you from the ieopardy of corporal dethe. where as yf ye had ben deed at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme / ꝑchaunce your ſoule ſholde haue ben in grete daunger of dampnacion / by the reaſon of deedly ſynne / in the whiche ꝑaduenture at ſuche tyme ye were culpable. Of your ꝓmyſed glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryficacion / how god of his charitable benignite hath predeſtynate you to be perpetuall inheredytare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdome of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / where as ye ſhall haue the fruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon
<pb facs="tcp:181163:16"/> and clere ſyght of his deyte / the whiche ſhall be more Ioye to you than my pen can wryte / herte can thynke / or mouthe can ſpeke. Remembrynge theſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche other / as it ſhall pleaſe god at that tyme to put in your mynde / gyue laudes and thankes to him / not onely for them: but alſo generally for all his other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfytes the whiche be innumerable. whan ye haue thus done / remember how vnthankfull and how vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynde you haue ben to hym / that dyde neuer before gyue hym due thankes for all ſuche his grete benyfy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / but mooſt vnkyndly forgetyng them haue offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded his mageſty by the reaſon of innumerable ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / the whiche ye haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted by all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tymes of your lyfe / Beſeche his grace tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mercy and forgyuenes knowlegyng your ſelfe to be a wretched ſynner / and of ſo grete fraylte that ye be neyther able of your ſelfe to pray deuoutly / nor to do any other good dede acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable to hym. Deſyre hym mekely and louyngly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll voucheſaufe to dyrect your prayer / ſo that it may be acceptable to hym / &amp; ꝓfytable to your ſelfe &amp; all other thynges neceſſary to be prayed for / ſayng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophete dauyd.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. cxi.</note> Dirigantur domine or<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o mea: ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cut incenſum in conſpectu tuo. Good lorde I beſeche the that my prayer may be dyrected &amp; aſcended in the ſyght of the / lyke to the ſwete odour of encenſe. Thus ordryng your ſelfe as I haue nowe ſayd / I truſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god that ye ſhall make a conuenyent <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon goyng before your prayer. And this take ye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt thyng that ſhall gyue you occaſyon of deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ¶The ſeconde thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall cauſe you deuoutely to pray is to remember fyrſt what nede &amp; neceſſyte ye ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue of prayer as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng your owne perſone. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayly
<pb facs="tcp:181163:16"/> what nede generally all the worlde hath. And thyrdly what nede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in the paynes of purgatory.</p>
            <p>¶Fyrſt I ſay it ſhall moeue you to pray deuoutly yf ye intyerly wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder what nede you haue of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer / as concernyng your ſelfe. For yf ye examyn your conſcyence depely / conſyderyng dyſcretely how your fraylte is moche i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clyned to pryde / to wrathe / to enuy to ſlouthe / to glotony / to auaryce / to lechery / &amp; to the ſpyces &amp; brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches of them. And on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary parte how ſlowe ye be to vyſyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyke ꝑſones / to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be deſolate &amp; lacke conſolacion / to gyue almes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore peple. &amp;c. And how tedyous it is for you to he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god priched / to here your maſſe &amp; other dyuine ſeruyce. And how ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnolent &amp; ſlep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye be ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ches ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s: I doubte not but ye ſhall wel perceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you had grete nede of prayer for your owne ꝑſone / &amp; that ſhall moeue you to pray deuoutly ¶Secondaryly I thynke that it wyll cauſe you to pray deuoutly yf ye conſyder what nede all the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hath of prayer. For as ſayth ſaynt Iohan the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> epyſtle.<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Mundus totꝰ in maligno po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitꝰ eſt. That is to ſay. all the worlde it ſet on vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſſe &amp; myſchefe. Not ſo to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery perſone in the worlde is ſo yll dyſpoſed. But that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny: &amp; it is to be feared leſt the mooſt parte be moche ſet to folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> concupyſcence of vyce &amp; ſynne. we knowe by dayly experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the people of the worlde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tue doth gretely decay / &amp; vyce doth dayly encreas &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typly. who is nowe lyuynge that euer ſawe or herde of me newe inuencyons of pryde and vanytees than is in theſe dayes? who herde euer of moo dyſceytes
<pb facs="tcp:181163:17"/> and fraudes among kynſfolkes and neybours? was the ſynne of the fleſſhe euer more vſed / ſythe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sodome &amp; Gomorre were dyſtroyed than it is now? was there euer greter ſwering &amp; blaſphemy than is now? It is taken but for a tryfle to ſwere by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woundes &amp; body of our ſauiour Ieſu Cryſt / &amp; by the maſſe / and by the gloryous ſacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auter. Alas for pyte / it wolde aſke to longe ſpace yf I ſholde reherce ſyngulerly by hymſelf euery grete notable vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is comynly &amp; dayly vſed in the worlde. But you my ſpyrytuall frendes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be more conuerſaunt in the face of the worlde than I am / maye ſe &amp; perceyue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che more abuſion / that I ceaſe to ſpeke of now bycau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe I wyll not tary ſo longe in this matter. But yf I ſhall ſpeke any thynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myniſtres of cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes chyrche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhold be adorned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grace and vertues to the example of other / I feare me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> among parte of them is alſo moche abuſion. who herde euer of more ſymony? who herde euer of more ſellyng of benefices vnder colour of penſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. who herde euer of more aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryce regnyng amonge ſeculer preſtes than is in theſe days? To ſpeke of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be reguler / who ſawe euer relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more remyſhly kept? who ſawe euer ſo many apoſtates that haue forſaken theyr relygyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; be now inſecular habite? And for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſyon to ſpeke general<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of perſones of euery faculte. who herde euer of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hereſy open &amp; ſuſpected than is in theſe dayes? Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke hede dyligent reder &amp; conſyder / whither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before reherſed / may now be veryfyed or not / where he ſayth. Mundus totꝰ in maligno po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitus eſt. The worlde is all ſet on ſynne. I thynke the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is no man that ꝓfoundly &amp; effectuouſly dooth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:181163:17"/> this generall myſery y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is vſed thrughe the mooſt parte of all the worlde / but it ſhall gyue hym occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pray deuoutly for amendement therof. And this for the ſeconde parte.</p>
            <p>¶Thyrdely to conſyder how grete nede the ſoules y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in the paynes of purgatory haue of prayer / wyl al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo ſubmynyſter plenteous &amp; habou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunt mater of de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For there they be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacyon or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort / in grete derkeneſſe &amp; myſery / ſuffryng paynes ineffable and contynually callyng &amp; cryenge for mercy / &amp; for to be releued with deuout prayers: &amp; other charytable dedes of good cryſtie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s yet lyuyng in this worlde. Oh what hert is ſo hard y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll not be mollefyed with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſyon vpon thoſe poore ſoules that there be in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes intollerable. It paſſeth the capacyte of all men ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gretenes of the paynes with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they be greuouſly tormented. After the mynde of ſome doctours theyr paynes be egall in comparyſon to the paynes of hell. Except that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes of hell be ꝑpetual / &amp; the paynes of purgatory temporal. There they be ſomtymes in extreme coldneſſe / &amp; ſomtyme in inextynguyble hoteneſſe. That hoteneſſe after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſom catholycall men / as ferre excedeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this elementary &amp; materyall fyre / as the hote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this fyre paſſeth the hoteneſſe of the fygura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyf fyre paynted on a walle. yf ony ſuche comparyſon may be made I wyll ſpeke no more of this mater / for I can not expreſſe / neyther in generall nor in ſpecyal what horryble paynes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be there ſuffre / and ſhal do vnto ſuche tyme as they haue made condigne ſatyſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for theyr treſpaces co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted / &amp; not ſuffyci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ently punyſſhed in this lyfe. Excepte they be releaſed
<pb facs="tcp:181163:18"/> by the deuoute prayers (as I ſayd before) &amp; by other good dedys of charitable criſtya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lyuyng yet in this worlde. wherfore euery deuout perſone before the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnyng of his prayer call to mynde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ineffable pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe ſoules do ſuffre / thynki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g yf he were ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how glad he wold be to be releaſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytes of ſuffrages &amp; prayers. This doyng I ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no man ſo colde nor ſo dull / but he wolde ſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re hym to the warmnes &amp; feruour of deuocyon.</p>
            <p>¶Now haue I ſhewed you after my poore maner of certayn meanes: the which well conſyderyng before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng of prayer wyll excytate &amp; moeue your hertes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feruent ſwetnes of deuocyon. yet I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by the helpe of Ieſus breuely to ſuꝑadde &amp; put one thynge more / &amp; ſo to make an ende of this mater. But peraduenture ſome men wyll thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am ſuꝑflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this poynt. for it wolde be very long &amp; tedyoꝰ to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre ſo many thinges euer tofore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynning of prayer. As to this obieccion I make this anſwere. If a man ſhold conſyder euery thyng at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> large as it is wryten it wolde aſke a longe ſpace. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effect of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a quycke memory may be ſo ſhortly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded that they ſhall not be tedyous / nor ony thyng gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous to ony ſuche whom it ſhall pleaſe to put them in practyſe. But yet for more compendyouſneſſe I wyl that all be not remembred at one tyme / and but ſomti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me one / and ſomtyme another / and ſo I thynke they wyll be tedyous to no man.</p>
            <p>¶Another meane that wyll gyue you occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to pray deuoutly / is tofore che begynnyng to thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eyther tofore your prayer be accomplyſſhed / or els as ſhortly as ye haue made an ende therof that ye ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:181163:18"/> departe out of this world / and be preſented to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right wyſe iuge / there to make a ſtreyte accompt and reke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of al the tyme of your lyfe paſt. But peraduentu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſom wyll ſay. why ſholde I thynke ſo? For I truſt to lyue many yeres longer. As to that I ſay not nay / but it may ſo fortune. Notwithſhandyng you beyng on lyue at the begynnynge of prayer / yf it ſhall pleaſe god / ye may departe tofore ye haue made a ꝑfyte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de therof. And yf I wold affirme this parte to be true there is no man lyuing that may truely affyrme the contrary. Therfore I holde it moche profytable thus for to thynke. And ſo doyng I truſt it wyll gyue you grete occaſyon to deuocyon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶How in tyme of prayer ſomtyme the mynde is moche dyſtracte by reaſon of wordely beſynes And remedyes for the ſame. Ca. v.iii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as example by euery thyng that is he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uy of the ſelf / or laden with ony thyng that depreſſeth the berer / ſooner &amp; more eaſely it may deſcende downe the hyll / than it may aſcend vp the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Prayer is an aſcencyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mynde to god as Damaſcene ſayth.<note place="margin">Li. iiii. ca xxiii pſ. xii.</note> Accordyng alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of the prophete in his pſalme ſayng. I haue lyft vp myn eyes vnto the mountes. That is to ſay. I haue made my prayer to the holy ſayntes in heuen / as meanes to god / of whom I truſt helpe and ſocoure. For my ſocoure and helpe is of god / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che made heuen and erthe. wherfore euery thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is heuy vnto the ſoule / dooth depreſſe the ſpyryte and letteth parfyte deuocyon / and cauſeth many &amp; often
<pb facs="tcp:181163:19"/> tymes diſtraccyon of mynde in tyme of prayer. Accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the ſayng of the Sapience.<note place="margin">Sapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie. j.</note> The body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupte doth greue &amp; let the ſoule / and the ſences do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe hym / whoſe mynde is occupyed aboute many thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges. For vndubted in tyme of prayer / there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is moche inclyned / where about in other tymes it is mooſt occupyed. If grete ſtudy / beſyneſſe / and care doth occupy the mynde / as to gete temporall ryches &amp; honours worldſy ꝓmocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: or other ſuche pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: no meruel yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoule can not be fyxed in one thing ſpecyally yf it be iner ſpyrytual. But prayer ſyth it is one of the partes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / yf it be pure / it hath reſpect onely or pryncypally vnto one thyng / which is god almyghty. To whom prayer bereth the pety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the hert / &amp; maketh ſupplicacyon for helpe. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hertes of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be occupyed in many thinges can not longe be fyxed on one thyng / wherfore theyr pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer can not be long pure without diſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mynd. Martha was occupyed about many thinges:<note place="margin">Luce. x</note> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhe was troubled in her mynde. But Mary occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyed about one / dyd chuſe the better parte. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhe was quyet in ſpyryte / &amp; all togyder conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue. Of the which example we may lerne / that ſith bothe theſe women were holy &amp; moche accept in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour of god: that the labours of them which ben pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lates &amp; take cure of other. and be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent for the loue of god to leue theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacyon / &amp; to take labours ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytual or temporall for theyr ſubgectes / ben moch me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytoryoꝰ. For albeit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue diſtraccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in theyr prayer / &amp; ſomtyme fele not ſuche ſwetnes &amp; flame of deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as they were wont to haue afore they dyde take y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offyce on them. yet let them be ſure: ſyth theyr
<pb facs="tcp:181163:19"/> labours is for god / &amp; helpyng of ſoules / ſo moch more ryche is theyr merytes afore god. how moch more is theyre labours &amp; cures? In ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders alſo / whiche dyſcretly and truely doth occupye the worlde for the mayntenyng of theyr houſhold / al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit they come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly haue dyſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of mynde in tyme of theyr prayer: yet they not wylling to haue ſuche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagacions of mynde: yf they often call in theyr mynd to the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of god they ſhal not leſe theyr me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte. For as ſaynt Thomas ſayth.<note place="margin">xxij. q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xxxiij. arti xi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Holy men haue ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme euagacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of mynde in tyme of prayer: And he ſayth moreouer that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſon dooth praye in ſpyryte &amp; trouthe / whiche moeued of the inſtinceyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt procedeth and gooth to pray. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for weykenes of ſpyryte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde afterward be wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dryng &amp; dyſtract. For whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde of hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dothe pray aſcendeth to god by contemplacion / than anone by cauſe it is feble &amp; weyke it falleth to euagacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deryng myndes. But holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes calleth in theyr ſpyryt to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre what they pray / &amp; ſo they contynue theyr deuocion. And this is one generall re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medy / &amp; as a dayly medicyn contynually to be vſed of euery perſone agaynſt dyſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of mynde / for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue theyr attencyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / deuocyon / &amp; meryte in prayer. Another remedy is ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes with actual intent (as moche as fraylte wyl ſuffre) to do theyr werkes and worldly beſynes to the honoure of god / actually refer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng them to his glory. As ſaynt Paule ſayth.<note place="margin">j. Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye eate or drynke / or what ſomeuer els ye ſhal do do al to the glory of god. This exercyſe of mynde vſed in other prayers / ſhal encreas the loue of god in theyr hertes / wherby thyer ſpyrytes ſhalbe more ſtrong in
<pb facs="tcp:181163:20"/> deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to auoyde grete diſtraccyons of mynde in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of prayer. And it wolde be noted of euery cryſten man that beſyde the naturall loue which he hath to his wyfe / chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſeruauntes / except in true catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chirch he endeuer himſelf by his good example of lyfe to edyfye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vertue / to the honour of god &amp; profyte of theyr ſoules / he ſhall do lytell more to his houſholde tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe the pagan or turke to his famylly. For they dayly do labour &amp; ꝓuyde for theyr houſholde / &amp; naturally dooth loue the ſame. But the faythfull ſeruaunt of god an true cryſtyans muſt do more. ¶Another remedy agaynſt diſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is this It is neceſſary for al ſuch honeſt worldly lyuers whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be moche troubled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcateryng mynde in prayer to apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf to ſome ordred exercyſe / ſpecyally in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche of god. As after they haue taken holy water knele downe in ſom place where they intende to reſt &amp; pray. And all worldly beſynes ſequeſtred all grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges agaynſt neyghbour al iniuryes / &amp; offences clene put out of mynde and remyt with meke and contryte ſpyryte / aſke god mercy for theyr vnkyndnes &amp; negli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces done &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myth ſyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt tyme they were there a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd for all vndyſcrete behauour &amp; impacyency to his houſhold &amp; neyghbours. And thanke god for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion of hym or his / &amp; all cryſten people. And for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefites of god / ſpecyally for your creacion / rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gloryficacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which we all truſt to haue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſones blyſſed paſſyon. whiche than lete vs call afore our mynde. and in ſure fayth depely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lame ſete vs mekely thank the father of heuen for his ineffable mercy / loue / &amp; charyte / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold ſende his eterne &amp; onely beloued ſone to ſuffe in our nature
<pb facs="tcp:181163:20"/> ſo paynfull &amp; ignomyneoꝰ a dethe to redeme man out of the thraldome of the deuyll. And alſo with all oure hertes thank our ſayd lord Ieſu cryſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone of god for his lyke loue / mercy / &amp; charyte. To whom (as ſaynt Poule ſayth.<note place="margin">Ad He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre. xii</note> Ioye &amp; glory profferd / all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſyon dyſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed) wolde ſuſtene the croſſe / &amp; ſuffre the mooſt payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dethe for our ſaluacyon. If we wolde thus ordre our ſelf in the chyrche dyſtraccyons ſholde haue lytell place in prayer. But yf the perſone be vnlettred &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che encombred with wandryng cogytacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theyr herte / than it is expedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for ſuch to haue afore theyr eyes ſome deuout remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or obiect / as ſome py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cture of the paſſyon of Cryſte / or ſome other ſaynt / to whome they haue mooſt deuocyon. That whyle ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes be ſtayed &amp; fyxed in that ſenſyble deuout ymage / theyr ſpyryte may more lyberally aſcende to god or to the ſaynt to whom they pray. And for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> conſyderacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ymages of ſayntes be ſet vp in the chyrches as bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That they redynge in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / theyr actes &amp; Ieſtes ſuffred for almighty god may be ſtyred to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocyon / and for to honoure god in his holy ſayntes. ¶Some vſeth agaynſt ſuche dyſtraccions lytell bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / in the whiche is conteyned pyctures of the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eles of the lyfe and paſſion of our lorde Ieſu / and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ouer theyr leues dooth worſhyp our lorde / ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng for euery article a Pater nr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / an Aue &amp; a crede. and this exerciſe is good for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche be vnlerned. &amp; I councell them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can haue no ſuche bokes to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the ſayd articles by the feeſtes of the yere. begynni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at the natyuyte of oure lorde god / his circumcyſion / his epyphany / his preſentacion in to the temple / his faſt and temptacyon / his dethe and bytter paſſyon / 
<pb facs="tcp:181163:21"/> his reſurreccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; aſcention / with other ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne feſtes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere. And for eche ſay the prayer aboue reherſed. And this done ſerue our lady lykewyſe / begynnynge at her concepcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / natyuite / ſalutacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / viſitacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / puri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; aſſumpcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And after this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles / mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: &amp; other holy ſayntes as theyr feſtes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be called to remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / or as they appere &amp; be reprynted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theyr ymages ſet vp in chyrches. This or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre vſed ſhall call in the mynde from worldly beſynes (&amp; ſo diſtraccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auoyded) it ſhall kyndle deuocyon / &amp; encreace the meryte and fruyte of prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of other maner of dyſtraccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And of the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and remedyes of theſame. Ca. ix.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be other diſtraccyons of mynde in ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of prayer / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe wherof is ſynne. For lyke as in bodyly ſekenes he is in grete ieo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pardy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dooth abhorre all meates: &amp; what ſo euer he receyueth he caſteth &amp; vomiteth it out agayn: ſo in lykewyſe he is mooſt ferre from de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocyon whoſe ſoule is mooſt ſore wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many &amp; dyuers mortall ſynnes. For very tedyous &amp; vnſauery is prayer and al ſpyrytual thynges to ſuch a perſone For yf ony tyme he begyn to pray / anone he hath do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / for he is ſo weyke in ſoule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can not contynue. He ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not taſte nor dygeſt ſpyrytuall thynges / bycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe in hymſelf he is all ſynfull and beeſtly. No maruell though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſone be dyſtract in prayer / whoſe herte is ſore wounded &amp; auerted fro god &amp; fro the lyfe of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce: I councell hym to ſeke for remedy betyme. Go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lauatory of helth / and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> contryte herte make clene &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:181163:21"/> hole confeſſyon. Take w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him ſo moche more huge con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tricion &amp; repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſorowe. How moche more by his ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he hath deſerued dampnacion / &amp; hath prouoked the wrathe / yre / &amp; indygnacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hye god omnypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent. Lete him neuer preſume / but thynke himſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy to come in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche / &amp; to appere in the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence of god with an vnpenitent herte. But rather w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the publycan for his ſynne iuge himſelf vnworthy to loke vp to heuen / &amp; bete that breſt and herte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his fyſt which hath ſo greuouſly offended / &amp; crye with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blycan. Mercy lorde god / mercy / mercy. A more ſure remedy or more holſome playſter for his ſores can he haue none. For lyke as it is a noble playſter or medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> healeth not onely the wounde / but alſo taketh a was the ſkar: whiche comynly is left in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe / ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tricion is a noble medycyn for the ſoule. For it may be ſo grete and parfite / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it not onely cureth the ſin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / but it maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to be in ſuche deteſtacyon / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it dooth awaye pryntes / fantaſies / ꝓnytees / yll cuſtomes / fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes / &amp; other vnclene mocions to ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / whiche ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e dooth leue behynde it in the ſoule / or at the leeſt dooth ſo myniſſhe them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moche they do not trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. For albeit that the contrycion of ſome is ſuffycient to the remyſſion of theyr ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es / yet it is not alway ſo ꝑfyte to take theſe foreſayd &amp; paynes &amp; effectes away and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſeth or is occaſion of fantaſies in tyme of pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer. For whan they wolde be moche deuout / and pra mooſt hertely. yea / ſomtyme in heryng maſſe / than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fantaſyes of theyr ſynnes is ſo brym<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in theyr eyes &amp; ymagynacion / that they haue no deuocyon to prayer And ſomtyme they leue theyr prayer / &amp; be ſo wery of ſuche cogitacions: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they feare themſelf leſt theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:181163:22"/> be not forgyuen / or that god dooth forſake them / &amp; is ſore dyſpleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and it is not ſo. For as ſaynt Gregory ſayth. Synnes remyt &amp; paſt / whan they be brought to memory / they neuer hurt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule / excepte they pleaſe them ſelf. As whan the ſoule hath delecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But yf ſuche perſones wold conſyder theyr owne ſelfe well / how they neuer dyd take ſuche payne &amp; penaunce / nor had ſo ꝑfyte contry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion &amp; ſorow for theyr ſynnes that it was able to put away all fantaſyes therof / they ſholde ſe that of very iuſtyce it were expedyent for them to haue ſuche tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For where they haue agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of god wylfully abuſed theyr owne wyll in ſuche ſynnes / it is the grete goodnes of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll ſuffre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyr payne agaynſt theyr wylles to be toſſed and vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fantaſies of the ſame ſynnes / to theyr meryte and crowne in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſyon to theyr gooſtly enmy whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hath no ferther power on them / than without pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryll to exercyſe &amp; trouble them onely with fantaſyes / whiche comynly is called the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of holy men. And therfore let them neuer leue theyr prayer nor pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce for them. So holy ſcrypture admonyſſheth ſayng. If the ſpyryte of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath power aſcende vpon the That is as the gloſe ſayth.<note place="margin">Eccle. x.</note> If a myghty temptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſayle the dymyt not &amp; leue not thy place for it. For the cure &amp; helthe whiche cometh therby in the ſoule / ſhall put away and make ceas the greteſt ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. For vndubted god dooth ſuffre the to be tempted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche fantaſyes for the mortificacyon of thy ſenſes: purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp; for due &amp; ꝑfyte ſatyſfaccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. ¶Remedyes agaynſt ſuch fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies. For theſe forſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s it is expedyent for ſuch ꝑſones neuer to
<pb facs="tcp:181163:22"/> leue theyr prayer / but go forth always ſpekyng holy wordes. For albeit they fele no ſwetnes in theyr wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſtly enmy feleth therof grete payne / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſhame. And if they ꝑceyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf ſore altered in theyr bodyes by ſuch thoughtes / arme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe &amp; make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually inuocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lorde for ſocour ſayng. Lorde thy bytter paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be betwene me and this temptacion. Some as they myght (theyr hertes fyxed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of our lorde) hath cryed &amp; named co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy name of Ieſu &amp; hath founde remedy / &amp; theyr te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacion hath ceaſed For lyke as euery thing is cured by his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary / &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perience ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taking ſtyckes fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre / it ſhall be ſone extynct &amp; que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched. So take away the cauſes &amp; vſe the contrary vertues of theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacions / &amp; all o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther diſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in prayer / &amp; they ſhall ceaſe. The cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of diſtraccions in prayer is not onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete enor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me lines as hereſy / homicide / vſury / &amp; other like / but alſo grete multytude of venyall ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp; generally all mortall ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es be occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; cauſes of dyſtraccyon.<note place="margin">. cor. iij</note> For albeit venial ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es taketh not grace away fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule yet where they be in cuſtome &amp; grete habou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the ſoul ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out grete labour attene to fele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwetnes of deuocyon. for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenſes hath ſo delyted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward &amp; ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyble pleſures: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can not ſauour nor taſte notably y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward ſwetnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiryt / which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit ſore deſyreth. Among all mortall ſynnes I note .vi. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpecyally dyſpoſeth to diſtraccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is pryde / e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uy / yre glotony / lechery / &amp; couetiſe. Pryde inclyneth to vayn glory / &amp; ypocriſy / &amp; to thoughtes of elacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf. for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud ꝑſones mynd is ſo beſy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whereſo euer he go or byde / ſtande or ſyt he ſpeketh to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf. And therfore
<pb facs="tcp:181163:23"/> he can do none otherwyſe in payer but whyles his to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue ſpeketh one worde his herte thynketh another And ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme he ymagineth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer was nor neuer ſhall be. ¶Remedy for theſe we maye ſoone haue / yf we in tyme of prayer wyl take good hede &amp; cuſtody of our herte / &amp; dyſpiſe all vaynglory &amp; prayſe of creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. abhorre ypocreſy / &amp; meke our ſelf to god. &amp; prepare our hertes ſpecyally in the begynning of prayer. For lacke of due preparacion in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge / &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are neglygent in orderyng our hertes to our prayer / cauſeth vs to haue lytell deuocion in our hertes / nor ſwetnes in our prayer. And contrary wyſe good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre in the begynnynge expelleth dyſtraccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: &amp; indu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceth feruour of ſpyrite. Example we may take of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iudith / which as ſcrypture ſheweth wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhold make her prayer to god / ſhe dyde caſt away all her gay aray / &amp; dyde clothe her ſelf with ſacke.<note place="margin">Iu. ix.</note> caſt duſt vpon her heed / and faſted &amp; watched in grete pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. ¶Of quene Heſter we rede alſo / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not onely ſhe dyd all theſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete wepyng &amp; waylyng. as it is ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the boke of Heſter / but alſo ſhe fyled her heed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> duſt &amp; donge.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. xiiij</note> And yede to euery place where ſhe had by her pryde &amp; myrth dyſpleaſed god. &amp; there ſhe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her heere in deteſtacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e.<note place="margin">Omeli. xxiij.</note> ¶Mary mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dalene alſo whan ſhe yede to here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy worde of our lordes prechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (as ſaynt Gregory ſayth) ſhe dyd take w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her ſo grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe made a ſacrefyce of eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry parte of her body / wherwith ſhe had offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd god If ſhe had this preparacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hert whan our lorde dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſpeke vnto her. no leſſe ought we to haue wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhall come in <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſence &amp; ſpeke to god whiche vndoubted we do as doctours ſayth / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we pray to him. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:181163:23"/> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malyce / &amp; impacyency ſholde be fer fro vs / which cauſeth dyſtraccyons of mynde in prayer / nothynge more. For Mary for the loue whiche ſhe had to god &amp; her neyghbour was worthy to here theſe wordes of our lorde / the grete multytude of her ſynnes be forgy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / bycauſe ſhe loueth moche / lete vs euer reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of our ſauiour.<note place="margin">Lu. vij</note> 
               <note place="margin">Ma. vi et. xviij</note> Except ye remyt eche other w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your hertes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your fader in heuen wyll not remyt nor forgyue your ſynnes. All theſe examples of theſe holy women ben wryten in the holy ſcrypture of god / and left for our exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple &amp; erudycion. Lete vs therfore with Mary magdalene whan we ſhal come to pray / wepe &amp; wayle our ſynnes. Call to our remembraunce with quene Heſter the tymes / the places / the perſones / and the partes of our body. And alſo the wordes / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dedes &amp; the thoughtes / in the which we haue offended the hye god omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; there teare our heere / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to be actually ſory for them &amp; haue them in deteſtacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and be dyſpleaſed with our ſelf / which ſo vnkyndly haue offended our mooſt louyng &amp; mercyfull fader in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And I prayſe it moche whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meke &amp; contrite herte ſpeketh to god in the moder tongue / prayſyng his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly name / or aſkyng mercy for his ſynnes. Nothynge tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde be ſo moche afore our eyes / nor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moche oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupy our hertes as heuen / whiche myſerably we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue loſt by ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. And hell to the which we haue bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de our ſelfe by ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perpetually except we ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacion. Lete vs therfore for cloth / clothe our ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſacke / as Iudith dyde / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye. Meke our ſelfe in our hertes: &amp; euermore reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber how vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy we be to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of god &amp; ſpeke to hym And in this exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of this holy woman we may lerne
<pb facs="tcp:181163:24"/> &amp; perceyue how lytel it pleaſeth god / or ꝓmoteth pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrch in gay apparel or clothing / ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we vſe our ſelfe warely therin. For nothyng mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re diſtracteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde / &amp; hurteth prayer &amp; deuocyon tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inordynate &amp; curyous affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; thoughtes of ſuche vanitees. ¶I wyll not ſay but it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy day to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orne our bodies honeſtly / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our myndes be not alienate fro god therby. Lete vs alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> quene Heſter caſt duſt &amp; do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our hedes. That is to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not onely howe we be mortall / duſt / aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes / &amp; erthe. &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> torne agayne we ſhall. But alſo caſt dong on our heed / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is knowlege of our ſelf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt vyle ſlynking &amp; vnkynd ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyueth. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> loke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtreight afore thyn eyes / &amp; iuge not thy neyȝbour / for in eaſe it is not lawfull for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. &amp; I ſuppoſe that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maye well thynke ſo on thy ſelf / whom onely in herte thou knoweſt &amp; no other. Many bycauſe theyr conſcyence murmures not / they thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf ſure / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a fals ſuerty. For as ſaynt Poule ſayth. I know no ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / but yet in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am not iuſtyfied. But the day of our lorde ſhall ſhewe &amp; declare what euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our myſerable ſoule ſhall be brought afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tribunall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hye iuge god almyghty / there to abyde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mooſt terryble ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice of god almyghty. Eyther to euerlaſtynge lyfe or endles payne. If we wold dayly exerciſe our ſelf in this maner of <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>paracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our prayer not onely we ſhold auoyde grete diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctyons of mynde but alſo we ſholde do due fruyte of penaunce for our ſynnes. Some there be whiche be moche lete in prayer by fantaſyes and dyuers thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes and cogytacyons and yet they be not moche intryked nor fyled wyth mortall ſynne. And the
<pb facs="tcp:181163:24"/> cauſe of theyr dyſtraccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſuppoſed to be grete habu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of venyall ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. For now a dayes many be gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to ſportes / games &amp; deſolate myrthe / &amp; ſpecyally to delycate fedyng of meates &amp; drynkes &amp; ydle ſpeche All which be poyſon to deuocion &amp; moch let to prayer &amp; occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies. For al ſuch diſſolute myrth / vayn ſpeche &amp; fedyng is ſo pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit / &amp; letteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule fro reioyſing in ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Auoyde this caſe &amp; deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil folow in prayer Delyte in ſuche vanytees / &amp; not onely ye ſhal droune deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. but alſo ye ſhal make your ſelf a ueſſell fyt for euery te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyon. Many ther be clene &amp; vncorrupte in body. but for lack of cuſtody of theyr hert fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for ſayd vyces hath fallen in to grete te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body / &amp; ſo hath ben ſore trobled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnclene thoughtes / ſpecially in tyme of prayer.<note place="margin">de ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bono. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> il j. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xxxviij</note> And al this is ſuffred of god / for to ſuppreſſe theyr pryde noryſſhed by ſuche fedyng &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolucyon. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grcte clerke <abbr>yſid</abbr> ſayth god ſuffreth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> proude ꝑſon bycauſe he wyll not ſe himſelf to fall in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptacion of lechery / which is ſo manyfeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſenſibly he may ſe his owne beſtlynes / &amp; ſo lerne to meke himſelf yet ſome there be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be cleue / &amp; bothe <abbr>vtuous</abbr> &amp; holy / &amp; yet be ſore troubled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche vnclene thoughtes &amp; ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body which trobleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſpecially in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of prayer.<note place="margin">ii. Cor xij.</note> &amp; this is ſuffred of god to kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes. So had ſaint Poule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his fleſſhe &amp; ſore was trobled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it / &amp; al was to kepe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / leſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete habu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of grace &amp; reuelacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhold make hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proud. wherfore ſuch fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies &amp; vnclene cogi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacions workith no hurt / where ther is no conſent to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for more profyte is the cuſtody and preſeruacyon of mekenes with exercyſe of temptacyon to the meke perſon than is hurte to haue ſometyme dyſtraccyon.
<pb facs="tcp:181163:25"/> Some be ſo dull in ſpyrite that albeit theyr conſcience dooth not moche reproue them of ſynne / yet they be very ſlowe to exercyſe themſelfe in vertue. And ſuche comynly be ſlepy &amp; ſluggyſſhe in theyr prayer. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe therof I ſuppoſe is not onely heuyneſſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexyon / but alſo by reaſon of hoteneſſe of conſcyence they thynke themſelfe ſure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. And ſo put not themſelfe to payne to labour for the encreaſe of grace &amp; deuocion / whiche ꝑadue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture they myght haue abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue other yf they wolde put theyr dylygece therto / for they haue leſſe impedymentes than other / &amp; that cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomtime to thynke in theyr hertes how they nede not to faſt / nor pray moche / nor watche / for they haue no grete ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. But all ſuche which be neyther colde nor hote / but rather do begyn to be lotheſome to our lorde as ſcrypture ſayth. I wolde aduiſe them to marke this poynt wel. Better it is after many fyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es remyt &amp; forgiuen ſtrongly to fyght for the loue of god &amp; for theyr owne ſaluacyon / than in fewe ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out batayle weykely to deſyre heuen.<note place="margin">Appoc. ij.</note> ¶In all theſe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraccions &amp; in ſuche otherlyke which cometh by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of ſekeneſſe or inordynate thought. Remoue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe and ye ſhall fynde remedy. But thoſe perſones whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be dull in ſpyrite I wolde counſell to vſe oftenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes depely ſome artycle or poynt of Cryſtes paſſion. ſuche as mooſt ſenſybly may moue them to deuocion. ¶Example who may conſyder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnſpekeable payne whiche the ſone of god dyde ſuffer for our ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es vpon the croſſe / where neyther ſtandynge vpon carpytes / nor ſyttyng vpon cuyſſhyns / but hangynge with all the weyght of his blyſſed body vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boyſtous nayles of yren / whiche dyde teare &amp; rent his handes and fete
<pb facs="tcp:181163:25"/> wherin were moſt ſynewes / vaynes: &amp; bones to his importable payne. And who may this in true faythe depely conſyder but it wyl ſtyre &amp; moeue hym to loue and deuocion / &amp; to take paynes for theyr owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me cometh of the fyre / ſo cometh deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of loue &amp; charyte. wherfore holy perſones ſholde be moche inwarde &amp; attent in the tyme of theyr pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer. For whan the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of deuocyon is tendre / ſomty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the leeſt caſt of the ſyght aſyde / or alienacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ony other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenſes may extinct it &amp; put it out. notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fyre of charyte remayneth in theyr ſoules: whiche yf they wyll labour &amp; blowe well by the exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſe of this forſayde holy poynt of our lordes paſſyon or ony ſuche other / they may kyndell and recouer the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayne to theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. which fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me yf they can not recouer / makyng theyr prayer in cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte / albeit they fele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe ſwetnes in prayer / yet ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuyng they ſhall not loſe theyr meryte.<note place="margin">iiii. ſen. di. xv.</note> As ſayth ſaynt Thomas &amp; other doctours mo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶How a man may ordre hymſelf in tyme of prayer. Ca. x.</head>
            <p>HEre before after my ſimple lerning I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſpoken of certayne meanes: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche vſed tofore the begynning of prayer may excitate &amp; gretely diſpoſe the mynde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feruour of deuocyon in the prayers folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. But it is oftentymes ſene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome men at the begynnyng of pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer be wel &amp; deuoutly diſpoſed. &amp; afterwarde as they procede theyr affeccyon decayeth / &amp; theyr deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynneth by lytell &amp; lytel to be colde. The cauſe of this
<pb facs="tcp:181163:26"/> as I ſuppoſe / is the multytude of fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſmes &amp; vayne thoughtes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which by the ſuggeſtion of our gooſtly enmy / wyll enterpryſe to haue poſſeſſion &amp; dominion in the ſoule of man / &amp; ſo to exclude the feruour of deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion &amp; ſpiritual affeccion. wherfore how to auoyde ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che vnprofityble cogytacions I ſhall ſhewe you a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche I thinke is very expedient for to vſe ¶This remedy I haue red in a boke of reuelacions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it pleaſeth god to ſhewe to a certayn holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>platyf fader. There he ſayeth he ſawe in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>placion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule of a Carthuſian aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted vnto heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a grete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pony of glorious au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels &amp; fayntes / where as it was magnyfice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly gloryfyed / for the manyfold vertuous dedes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vſed in the tyme of his lyfe paſt. but in ſpecyall he had one grete accidentall rewarde bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vſed in the tyme of ſayng his ſeruice for euery verſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſayd / to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blyſſed wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of our ſauiour Ieſu cryſt mooſt ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſly bledi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as hangyng on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wold haue my ſpyrytuall frendes to vſe agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne &amp; vnprofytable cogitacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in tyme of prayer wyll im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portunely knocke at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of our hertes. Vnto this councelleth the holy apoſtle ſaynt Peter in the .iiij. chapyter of his fyrſt epyſtle / ſayenge. Chriſto igitur paſſo in carne: &amp; vos eadem cogitatione armamini. Seynge that Chryſt ſuffred paſſyon in his paſſyble body / loke that ye vſe the remembraunce of the ſame as a ſtronge armour or defence. The remembraunce of this blyſſed paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may well be called a ſtronge ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mour. For it is ſo ſtronge and of ſuche vertue / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt it there can none of our mortall enemyes (that is to ſay neyther the world / nor the fleſſhe / nor the deuyll)
<pb facs="tcp:181163:26"/> preuayle nor haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyctory. But whanſo euer we be mooſt troubled with them / yf we cal this to myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / they wyll anone vanyſhe away / as doth the ſmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of fyre in the ayre.</p>
            <p>¶There is no te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacions: no trybulacions. nor none other aduerſytees that may haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better or vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande of this. And therfore ſaynt Auguſtyn on this maner ſpeketh of hymſelfe: In omnibus temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibꝰ. &amp;c. In all temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / trybulacions / and aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſytees I fynde neuer ſo efficacial and ſure remedy as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blyſſed wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of our ſauyour Ieſu cryſt. wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore deuout chryſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I wyll exhorte and aduyſe you in all trybulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: whyther they be ſpyrytuall or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall / to arme you with this impenetrable harneys of the paſſyon of Cryſt. That is to ſay / with de memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of this blyſſed wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. And not onely in the tyme of aduerſite / but alſo in proſperyte. And mooſt ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally / as nowe for my purpoſe I wyll councell you to vſe this medytacyon or reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce in tyme of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. For very harde it is / and almooſt impoſſyble for any man the whyche dooth not vnderſtande (at the leeſt) the lytterall ſence of his prayer / for to kepe his mynde contynully eleuate and lytte vp to almyghty god in deuocyon / and vpon the due cyrcumſtaunces therof. wherfore neceſſyte wyll cauſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell hym to admyt ſome other cogytacyons and thoughtes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyde the ſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayer. But ſo it is that euery man ſholde eſchewe and put from hym at all tymes / but mooſt ſpecially in tyme of prayer vnfruytfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>profitable thoughtes / and kepe his mynde ſtedfaſtly as moche as he may vpon good ſpiritual thoughtes
<pb facs="tcp:181163:27"/> but as I ſuppoſe there is none more ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all / nor more fruytfull than is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> medytacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of Cryſt wherfore I wyll councel you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be vnlerned &amp; ꝑceyue not the lyterall ſence of your prayer. &amp; alſo I holde it profytable for you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be lerned in the tyme therof to let your mynde be occupyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of theſe precious wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. If ye thus do / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ye exclude the vayne &amp; vnprofytable cogitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of worldly thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Than ſhall ye be moche quyet in your ſoules fro te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of your ghoſtly enmyes. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ye be fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And than ſhall ye offre vp to god your prayer more odoriferous / more ſwete / &amp; more accepta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to hym / than is the fragrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fume of incenſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>¶How after prayer wyl folow te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neglory. And how they may be eſchewed &amp; auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by dyuers remedyes. Ca. xi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hortly after this maner of deuout prayer or els in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme therof your ghoſtly enmy wyl be beſy to tempt you to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyce of vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neglory / &amp; ſo (yf he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) cauſe you not onely to leſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merite of your deuout prayer / but alſo beſyde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greuouſly to offende god / by the reaſon of this deteſtable ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. wherfore it is nedeful to be cyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect. &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ꝑceyue your ſelf to be aſſayled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s anone mekely ſubdue your ſelf to god / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feynedly knowlegyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf ye haue prayed deuoutly it is your duty ſo to do. And yet be nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g able ſo to do as of your ſelf / but onely it cometh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete goodnes &amp; grace of almyghty god. That we can do nothyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good is / as of our ſelfe doth wytnes ſaynt Poule ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng.
<pb facs="tcp:181163:27"/> No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſumus. &amp;c.<note place="margin">ii. co. iii.</note> we be not ſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as of our ſelfs to thynk ony good thought / but all our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy is of god. That all thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is good cometh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god it appereth wel by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame apoſtle in another place where he ſayth that he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more labour in <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>chynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worde of god tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other apoſtles. But than he quyckly ſomthi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe wordes ſayth. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ego: <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:absed"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>sed</ex>
               </expan> gr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a dei mecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It was not I. but it was the grace of god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me. Ryght ſo my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted to vaynglory / eyther for ſayng of your prayers deuoutly / or for doyng ony other good dede / quickly make anſwer to your goſtly enmy / ſayng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Poule. It was not I y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyd this good dede / but it was the grace of god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me. And by this meane keping your ſelfs in mekenes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay Hertely knowlegyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no goodnes cometh of our ſelf but it cometh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god / ye ſhal not onely haue the meryte of your deuout prayer / but alſo ye ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue a crown in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyctory of your goſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my / by reſiſting of his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. But it fortuneth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tymes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath by the grace of god &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nes as I haue now ſayd / reſyſted a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vaynglory. by &amp; by there foloweth an other te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vyce more ſubtylly &amp; moch more craftely than dyd the fyrſt. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath reſiſted one te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſayd vaynglory / the deuyl wyll be redy caſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde of the reſiſtent / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath done a noble acte / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is worthy to haue a grete rewarde of god with ſuche other flateryng cauyllacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche be more peryllous than the fyrſt. And after theſe yf they be reſyſted / ꝑadue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture he wyl multyply mo / in ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll trouble the deuout man ſo ſore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:181163:28"/> vnnethe know what is beſt for hym to do. but I wyl aduyſe euery ſwete ſoule to be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort / &amp; ſtrong in god / takynge ſuche importune temptacyons as a ſcourge or flagellacyon for his ſynnes paſt / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he hath greuouſly offended almyghty god. And thogh he be ſore troubled therwith / yet let hym euer haue a conſtant purpoſe to reſyſte / as moche as ſhall lye in hym / makynge the ſygne of the croſſe in his for heed / and callyng to remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the bleſſed woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of our ſauyour Ieſu chryſt. And than call to hym ſayng as dyde his dyſcyples. Mathei octauo. whan they were troubled with tempeſtes vpon the water Domine ſalua nos: perimus. Saue vs good lorde / or elles we ſhall peryſſhe. ¶He that wyl thus do / let hym truſt ſurely to haue remedy. And truely he ſhall not fayle therof / but quickely he ſhal be delyuered fro the ieopardous tempeſt of temptacyon. or elles haue grace / ſtrength / &amp; paciently to ſuffre them. And after this lyfe gloryfyed in the kyngdome of heuen. For he ſayth by the mouthe of his prophete. Pſalmo. lxxxx. Quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in me ſperauit: liberabo eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. Bycauſe he truſteth in me I wyll delyuer hym. I wyll defende hym bycauſe he dyd know my name. He cryed on me and I ſhall graciouſly here hym. I am w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym in his trybulacion / from the whiche I ſhall take hym &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryfy hym. ¶Alſo the apoſtle ſaynt Paule in his fyrſt epyſtle vnto the Corynthyens ſpeketh to the conſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of ſuche perſones that be moche troubled with te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyons ſayng. Hidelis aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deus. &amp;c. Almighty god is faythfull the whiche wylt not ſuffre vs to be tempted forther than he wyll gyue vs grace for to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſt. But in tyme of temptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wyll gyue you gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce
<pb facs="tcp:181163:28"/> to reſyſt / &amp; alſo torne it to your grete ſpyrytuall pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte. ¶Alſo ſaynt Bernard ſayth in his fyfth ſermon de quadrageſima. Sub te eſt o homo appetitꝰ tuꝰ. &amp;c O man / ſayth he: thyn appetyte is vnder thyn owne gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and thou art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord of it. Thy enmy may moeue thy to temptacyons / but it is in thy lybertie whyther thou wylte conſente or not. whan he tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth the to pryde / vaynglory / glotony / vanite / impa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyence / lechery / or ony ſuche other / loke y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And as ofte as thou doeſt reſyſt / ſo oft thou ſhalt be crowned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crownes of glorye. to the which bryng vs / be that on the croſſe dyed for vs. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶How the fynall intent of our prayers ſhold be the laude &amp; prayſe of god. And how he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſyre in prayer all other thynges neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly referrynge them to this ende. Ca. xij.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed almighty god of his infynit good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe to creat &amp; make man to his ymage and ſymilytude y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he &amp; his poſteryte myght ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the places in heuen / fro whens / Lucyfer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his adherentes dyde fall for theyr pryde. for the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may perpetually giue laudes and prayſe to theyr maker w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the gloryoꝰ au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels in heuen wherfore my deuout frendes we ſholde refer our pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yers: &amp; all other good dedes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall haue grace for to do fynally to this ende. Not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng we may lawfully deſyre in our prayers all thynges neceſſary and expedyent bothe to our ſoules / and alſo to our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes. Hauynge euer in purpoſe the fynall intent / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche I ſpake before. After the mynde of the ſwete and mellyfluous doctour holy ſaynt Bernard ſaynge
<pb facs="tcp:181163:29"/> in his ſermon before ſayd. All thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we nede to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre in prayer / may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude in .iij. peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Of the whiche one perteyneth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body / another to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule / the .iij. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beatitude of the lyfe eternal. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perteyneth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of man we may lawfull<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deſyre of god all thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be neceſſary therto / as meate / drynke / &amp; clothes: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche other / by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſuſteyned in holy ſeruyce. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conde peticion we may deſyre in prayer all thyng ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our ſoules: as for grace &amp; vertues. &amp;c. &amp; for theſe we ſholde pray oft / deuoutly / &amp; feruently. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſholde deſyre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; loue to haue the lyfe eternall. For the ende (as I ſayd before) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may vnceaſyngly laude &amp; prayſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> magnyfice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lorde / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyde create &amp; make vs to his lykenes. But in theſe. iii. peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s it is neceſſary to obſerue .iii. thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges. For in the fyrſt many tymes there is ſuꝑfluite / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de impurete / &amp; in the .iij. elacyon or pryde. For oft ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes we deſyre to haue ſuper fluite &amp; more than is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall thynges. And ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme we deſyre to haue vertues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may make oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or hoſte our ſelfs therein. And ꝑadue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme we ſeche how to obteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe eternall. Not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> humylyte &amp; mekenes but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a fals co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in our own meries or deſeruin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Therfore we muſt take hede whan we pray for te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we deſyre no more but as neceſſite requyreth. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we pray for vertues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fro i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>purete / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we deſyre not vertues to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke oſtentacyon &amp; boſtyng therof. And whan we pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe eternall / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we nothyng preſume of our own merytes or deſeruynges: but onely on the grete mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; goodnes of god. ¶And to my purpoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold
<pb facs="tcp:181163:29"/> referre all theſe fynally to the laude &amp; prayſe of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyde create &amp; make vs / it appereth well by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ſaynt auguſtin i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his .x. omelye where he ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no true cryſtyan ſholde deſyre to haue all te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall &amp; tranſitory thinges. But all the effect of his intencion &amp; prayer ſholde be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall beatitude where as he maye laude &amp; prayſe his creatour &amp; maker ꝑpetually w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all glorious ſayntes. And whan it pleaſeth god to gyue vs te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall goodes accordynge to our prayers / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold we gyue him due tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; whan it pleaſeth him to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro vs: yet neuertheles ſhold we thanke him. And in this parte kepe vs indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tendted whan it ſhall pleaſe him to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro vs. but lete vs pray deuoutly / hertely / inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neuer take him himſelfe nor his grace fro vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶For whome we ſholde pray. Ca. xiii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a laudable cuſtom in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chirche of Cryſt to pray for thre ſtates or degrees: in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned ſuche ꝑſones for whome it is neceſſary to pray. That is to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the temporalte / &amp; the ſoules in purgatory. The chirche dooth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs to pray for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for they haue no nede therof. Nor for the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in the paynes of hell / for to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer can not pro fyte. But we ſholde pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in this worlde ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge / &amp; for the ſoules y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in purgatory. ¶Fyrſt we ſholde pray for the ſpiritualte / as for our holy fader y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his ſubgectes: myniſtres of the chirche / &amp; ſpecially for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop our dyoceſan / &amp; ſuche as vnder him hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure of our ſoules: Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darily we ſholde
<pb facs="tcp:181163:30"/> pray for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poralte / &amp; ſpecially for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges grace / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all ſuche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnder him be rulers &amp; gouerners of the realme. And in this parte euery man (yf he be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralte) ought pricipally to pray for himſelf. And yf he be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>alte lykewiſe to do in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> parte / &amp; than for his parentes: kynſfolkes: &amp; bn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fanctours / &amp; than gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally for all other chriſtianes: bothe good and bad (as ſayth ſaynt Auguſtyn in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnyng of his thyrde ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xij. ſonday after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trynite.) For the good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may ꝓfyte &amp; encreas in goodneſſe. For the bad y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may haue grace to amende. ¶Alſo well done it is to pray for heretykes &amp; infydels: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may haue grace to forſake theyr errours &amp; infidelite / &amp; be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; brought to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veryte of cryſten fayth. &amp; Beſydes theſe our ſauiour cyryſt byddeth vs pray for our enmy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do ꝑſecute and trouble vs. And ſurely ſo we haue grete cauſe. For yf we take theyr perſecuryons pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god / they ſhall gretely augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas our crownes &amp; rewardes in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a ſhort co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion in this parte / we ſholde pray gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally for all thynges neceſſary to be prayed for.</p>
            <p>¶Thyrdly we ſhold pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of purgatory / &amp; therfore it is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">i. machab. i</note> Scta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ergo &amp; ſalubris cogitacio. &amp;c. It is an holy &amp; a holſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought to pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be deed / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne infilicte for theyr ſynnes. And ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſtyn ſayth in his .xliiij. ſermon ad fr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es in Heremo. Ora ergo ꝓ defu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctis. &amp;c. Pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be deed. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe eternall / they wyl not forgette to pray for you. But it theſe dayes there be many heretykes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaye and affyrme that there is no purgatory / in the whiche the ſoules of them that then
<pb facs="tcp:181163:30"/> departed fro this lyfe be purged fro the fylthneſſe of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. But anone as they departe they go eyther to he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen or to hell. I myght bryng in dyuers auctorytees of holy ſcrypture to confute this falſe opynyon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / but as now I wyll lete them paſſe / partely bycauſe that<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of late catholycall &amp; grete famous clerkes in theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes lately compyled: hath confuted ſuche opynyons moche more ſtrongly than my ſymple lerning is able to do. And partely bycauſe it was my purpoſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnyng to wryte this poore treatyſe as an erudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of prayer to ſuche as haue but ſmall or none vnder ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng in holy ſcrypture / &amp; not as a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futacion of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retykes. But I wyll beſeche you all my ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for whome I haue taken this laboure / in the blyſſed woundes of our ſauyour Ieſu Cryſte / yf ye here any ꝑſones ſpeke eyther of this / or of any ſuche other falſe erronyous opynions: that ye gyue to them no creden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / nor argue ye not with them in the cauſe yf they be lerned &amp; pe vnlerned / leſt peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture they myght ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce your intellygence by ſubtyll argumentes: appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng to your naturall reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they were true / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is the contrary. But rather withdrawe your <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce fro theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany / dyſcuſſing nothyng in your myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that excedeth your lernyng / but mekely and ſtedfa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtly beleue as the chyrche of Cryſt dooth inſtruct you And as holy doctours and ſayntes inſpyred with the holy gooſt hath left here behinde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on this erthe for our erudicion. ¶I wyll ſpeke nomore of this matter now / but torne agayne to my purpoſe / deſyring you ouer in your deuout prayers to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the ſoules in purgatory &amp; ſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of your pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and frendes / and benefactours. And of youre
<pb facs="tcp:181163:31"/> benigne charite for thoſe ſoules y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche I your poo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; beedman am mooſt bounden to pray for. And generally for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules in purgatory / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wyll pleaſe almyghty god of his infynyte mercy to releaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro theyr paynes &amp; take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his grete glory and ioye / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame god omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vs all immedyatly after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we departe fro this lyfe. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>¶How he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll haue his prayer aſcende to god muſt make it .ij. wynges. Ca. xiiij.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. lx. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynt Auguſtin ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſo euer wyll haue his prayer fle or aſcend to god / muſt <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pare for it .ij. winges: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / faſting &amp; almes dedes. And ſaynt Bernard in his fourth ſermon vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiphany of our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de affirmeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / callyng theſe .ij. wynges afflyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the fleſſhe / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt or dyſpyſyng of the worlde And though theſe .ij. doctours differ in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes: yet do they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corde in the ſignificacion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For faſtyng is an afflyccion or punyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe / &amp; gyuing almes is a dyſpiſing of the worlde. For ye ſhall ſe but fewe men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath grete affeccion &amp; loue to the goodes of the worlde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll vſe moche to gyue almes. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe affeccion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man hath to worldly godes: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more large wyll he be in gyuynge almes. Theſe doctours do ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan a deuout prayer hath theſe .ij. winges it wyll fle into heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſwyftly / and there w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubt it ſhal gracyouſly be herde. wherfore I wyll exhort eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry deuout ꝑſone dyſcretely to vſe faſtyng &amp; gyuing of almes. But ꝑchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl ſay to me. I am ae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged or gretely diſeaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infyrmytees &amp; ſekeneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:181163:31"/> may not faſt. Alſo I am ſo poore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am not able to gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue almes / how tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde I <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pare theſe .ij. wynges for my prayer? ¶As to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt I make this anſwere ſayng / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; faſting was not ordeyned for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as be of grete aege / nor for ſuche as be moche vex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infyrmytees. But it was ordeyned for ſuche ꝑſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as be luſty &amp; ſtronge to ſubdue &amp; chaſtyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuꝑflu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous fyerſnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes therof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all appetites may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better ſubgected vnto reaſon. Wherfore yf you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be aeged or vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmitees ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a good mynd to faſt if ye were able therto. I doubt not but almighty god wyl accept your good wyl / as yf ye dyde ꝑforme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing in dede. This I ſpeke of cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall abſtinence or bodyly faſtyng. But there is ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther called ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to abſtene fro vyces &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ben accuſtomed by a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>long ſeaſon. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is olde or ſeke may kepe this abſtyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / as wel or better than he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> luſty &amp; ſtrong. And this euery true cryſten man is bounde to kepe as wel the olde as the yong / the ſeke as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole. The other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay corporall abſtinence is ordeyned as for a meane or helpe to this. The other is good &amp; profitable for ſuche as be able to kepe .ij. but this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better &amp; more ꝑfite &amp; it ſhold be obſerued of euery ꝑſon. wherfore yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde &amp; ſeke ꝑſones kepe this abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in dede / &amp; the other in wyll / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wolde be glad to kepe it yf they were able / it is not to be feared but they do ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pare this one wyng of prayer. And yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ꝑſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be luſty &amp; ſtrong in theyr bodyes do wyſely &amp; diſcretely obſerue bothe corporall &amp; the ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all abſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do they alſo on theyr parte well <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pare this one wynge of prayer. ¶As to the ſeconde where the
<pb facs="tcp:181163:32"/> ſeke man ſayth he is ſo poore that he is not able to gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue almes. I make this anſwere / ſayng that (after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde of ſaynt Auguſtyn) there is .ij.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ia. xlii</note> maner of almes the one is to forgyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hertely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath offended you Or (after ſaynt Gregory) to gyue inſtruccyon of <abbr>vtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</abbr> to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ignorant / to gyue councell to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue nede therof / to gyue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacion to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les / &amp; ſo forth of other lyke. And this maner of almes he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in pouerte (for te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral goodes) maye gyue as largely as he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath grete rycheſſe &amp; worldly ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. The other almes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaynt Auguſtyn ſpeketh of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is to gyue meate to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hongry / drynke to the thyrſty / clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naked. &amp;c. To giue this almes cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celeth vs our lorde ſpekyng by his prophete yſay / where he ſayth. Frange eſurienti pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lviii.</note> that is to ſay. Breke thy brede to hym that is hongry. Gyue hoſpytalyte to the poore people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> labour in iourney. And whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is naked / giue him clothes. It belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth ſpecially to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryche man to gyue this almes / but not onely to hym. For the poore man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath but lytell ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / yf he gyue parte of that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good wyll he ſhal haue as grete a rewarde of god / as the ryche man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gyueth grete &amp; large almes. And this appereth well by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of our ſauiour Cryſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell of Luke where he ſayeth / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the poore woman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offred but .ij.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xxi.</note> mynutes: the whiche be a ferthyng / offred more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the ryche men dyde. And yet euery one of them by large gyftes dyde offer. And yf a man be ſo poore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath nothyng / yet yf he haue onely a good mynde / &amp; wolde be glad for the loue of god to gyue almes yf he had worldly ſubſtaunce / his mynde wyll be accepted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dede. Now than it appereth will that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:181163:32"/> bothe poore and ryche may gyue almes both ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally and corporally as I haue beforeſayd. wherfore my deuout frendes I wyll exhorte you to folowe the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of the holy man Choby / where he ſayth.<note place="margin">ca. iiii.</note> Ex ſubſtantia tua fac elemoſina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. Of thy ſubſtaunce lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> gyue almes / &amp; torne not thy face away fro any poore man that dothe aſke the / and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our lorde wyll not torne his face fro the. Haue mercy and pyte on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore / &amp; gyue to them almes as thy goodes wyl extende. If thou beryche &amp; haue grete ſubſtaunce gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue than a large almes. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue but lytell yet gyue parte therof as thou mayeſt / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good wyll. If thou haue nothyng / yet at the leeſt loke that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue a good mynde. This doyng thou ſhalt prepare for the a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te rewarde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of neceſſyte. For almes wyll dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the from all ſynne / and from dethe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhold folowe there vpon. And it wyll not ſuffer this ſoule to come in derkenes / but it wyll gyue the a grete hope &amp; truſt of ſaluacion / whan thou ſhalt appere to fore the face of god omnypotent. ¶Alſo vnto this exhorteth vs our mayſter Cryſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xi. chapytre of Luke / ſayng. Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te elemoſinam: et ecce omnia munda ſunt vobis. Giue ye almes / and than all thinges be clene to you. For it is wryten. Elemoſina reſiſtit peccatis.<note place="margin">Eccle. iii.</note> Almes doth reſiſt vyce and ſynne. wherfore it foloweth in the .vij. chapytre. Elemoſinamfacere ne deſpicias.<note place="margin">Ca. xxxi</note> Dyſpyſe not to gyue almes / but as it foloweth. Conclude ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſinam in ſinu pauperis. &amp;c. Pryuely put thyne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in to the boſom of the poore man / and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it wyl pray for the to god. For as it is in the .iii. chapytre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame boke. Sicut aqua extinguit igne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. Lyke as water dooth quenche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre / ſo almes dooth quenche
<pb facs="tcp:181163:33"/> the payne ordeyned for ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. wherfore my intierly be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loued fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des I wyll aduyſe you to vſe oft tymes to gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue almes as I haue ſayd tofore. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhall ꝑfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely make the ſeconde wynge of prayer. The whiche prayer ſet about with the other wynge of abſtynen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and this wyng of almes wyll aſcende &amp; fle quykly vnto the celeſtyall countre / &amp; there prepare for you a manſyon or dwellynge place / in the whiche ye ſhall reſt perpetually / with all blyſſed au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels and ſayntes gyuyng reuerence &amp; honour / lande and prayſe vncea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyngly / to the mooſt gloryous Trynite. Cui ſit honor et gloria per infinita ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth the treatyſe called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pomander of prayer.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprented at London in the Feteſtrete / at the ſygne of the Roſe garlande / by Robert Coplande. The yere of our lorde. M.CCCCC.xxx. the .xxxi. day of October.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Copland (McKerrow 77)</figDesc>
                  <head>Robert Coplande.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:181163:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
